<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ascents of the soul, or, David's mount towards God's house being paraphrases on the fifteen Psalms of Degrees / written in Italian, by ... Gio. Francesco Loredano ..., 1656 ; render'd into English, Anno Dom. 1665.</title>
            <title>Gradi dell'anima. English</title>
            <author>Loredano, Giovanni Francesco, 1607-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 212 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49178</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6897</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12988545</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12988545</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64837</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49178)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64837)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 719:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ascents of the soul, or, David's mount towards God's house being paraphrases on the fifteen Psalms of Degrees / written in Italian, by ... Gio. Francesco Loredano ..., 1656 ; render'd into English, Anno Dom. 1665.</title>
                  <title>Gradi dell'anima. English</title>
                  <author>Loredano, Giovanni Francesco, 1607-1661.</author>
                  <author>Coleraine, Hugh Hare, Baron, 1606?-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 60 p., 1 leaf of plates.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.G. and J.P. for Robert Harford ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translated by Hugh Hare, Baron Coleraine.  Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 56.</note>
                  <note>Translation of Gradi dell'anima.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXX-CXXXIV --  Paraphrases, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:64837:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>elaborate iconographic scene viewed by man writing in book</figDesc>
                  <q>Gen. 28. cap. a 16 ad fin.</q>
                  <q>Heb. 13. cap. 14:15:16</q>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>view of a City by the sea</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>depiction of Jacob's ladder (Genesis 28.11-16)</figDesc>
                        <q>Ἀπ ἄρτι ὄπσεσθε τον οὐρανὸν 
ἀνεφγότα 
καὶ τουσ ἀγγέ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>λουσ

του Θεου
ανα<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>βαινοντασ
καὶ καταβαι<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>νοντασ επι  
τον υιὸν τοῦ ανθρωπου<bibl>Joan. 1.52.</bibl>
                        </q>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>depiction of Jacob's altar at Bethel (Genesis 28.17-22)</figDesc>
                        <p>Bethel</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>inset seal of (?) the Lion of Judah</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <signed>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>monogram</figDesc>
                     </figure> Design.</signed>
                  <byline>W. Faithorne Sculp</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64837:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ASCENTS OF THE SOUL: OR, DAVID's Mount TOWARDS GOD's Houſe. BEING PARAPHRASES ON THE FIFTEEN PSALMS of DEGREES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written in</hi> Italian, <hi>By the Illuſtrious</hi> GIO. FRANCESCO LOREDANO, <hi>a Noble</hi> Venetian, 1656. Render'd into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> Anno Dom. 1665.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Né ſi comincia ben, ſe non dal Ciélo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. G.</hi> and <hi>J. P.</hi> for <hi>Robert Harford,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:64837:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64837:2"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>decorative headpiece</figDesc>
               </figure>
To the moſt Honour'd LUCINDA.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the kind Sun (which cheers our dying Muſe)</l>
               <l>From the bright Eaſt, brings day, and with it, views</l>
               <l>The World's fair Parts; but finding none ſo ſweet</l>
               <l>As th' Orient Beauties, whom he firſt did greet;</l>
               <l>Back to his Morning Miſtreſs he doth run;</l>
               <l>Ending his round Heat there, where he begun.</l>
               <l>So, though my Rhimes, like ſtragling Waters, fled</l>
               <l>From Wit's clear Spring; from You, the Fountain's Head;</l>
               <l>Yet now my Fancy pays its final Stream</l>
               <l>To its firſt <hi>Helicon,</hi> and faireſt Theam.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For ſure, 'tis Heav'n's, with your bleſt Influence,</l>
               <l>('Tis not th' Extream's uſual Coincidence)</l>
               <l>Which as it did at firſt our Verſe Baptize;</l>
               <l>So now redeems Theſe from Idolatries.</l>
               <l>That their late wand'ring Feet no more may roam;</l>
               <l>But (like the elder Brothers) keep at home.</l>
               <l>While You reſtore our Muſic, and renew</l>
               <l>Our Mind, to ſing again to God, and You.</l>
               <l>See here our Muſe waſhes her Feet, and all;</l>
               <l>Turns Penitent, that had been Prodigal:</l>
               <l>And as a <hi>Magdalen,</hi> with all her Store,</l>
               <l>She worſhips Goodneſs; but doth waſt no more.</l>
               <l>She ſends her Honey back, to that dear Hive,</l>
               <l>Where ſhe'll be bury'd, (if not kept alive.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then with her Notes, (Swan-like) ſhe'll end her Days,</l>
               <l>Singing Your Worth, her <hi>Requiem,</hi> and God's Praiſe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:64837:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64837:3"/>
            <head>To the moſt Honour'd LUCINDA.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU may ſmile, while I bluſh, that You find me ſpeak in Print, when You know I love no ſuch phraſe or thing; becauſe it argues an affectation, which I have not 'till now, been guilty of. But ſince it is too general a Diſeaſe, that Poverty and Lazineſs bring upon <hi>Linguiſts;</hi> no wonder if my Converſe with ſome ſuch, hath infected me at this time, when remembering how I uſed from beyond Seas to Congratulate Your <hi>New-year</hi> with ſome Foreign Preſent: And finding none of that Store left by me, (which was dearly bought, and far fetch'd) I turn'd from my Cabinet, to my Cloſet, and there found this <hi>Venetian</hi> Chryſtal, ſo finely wrought and polliſhed by the Author, and not ill ſet (perhaps by my putting a File unto it) as I was reſolved to make an Offering of it to that Shrine Your Oratory, wherein are many things worth the admiring; but none more than the pious behaviour of Your ſelf.</p>
            <p>This is ſo excellently uſeful, as that we may be pardoned for deſiring a Reflection of it. And therefore, Madam, I ſend this <hi>Mirrour of Devotions,</hi> not to direct or dreſs Yours; but to diſplay them unto others, and to do my Duty ſo far to all the Good; as to do You Right in the diſcovery of ſo rare a Goodneſs as Yours is; which hath not only embolden'd me to venture up the Stairs to Your Praying-place, and to reviſit theſe Degrees, (whereon I went above ten Years ago) but likewiſe to ſhew the World how Your Piety is exemplary like <hi>David</hi>'s; it hath led and inſtructed a numerous Train to follow You (though very hardly) up a great way towards the Mountain of <hi>Holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, Madam, ſince this Age doth want ſuch Preſidents in Worth, in Goodneſs, and in Place, as Your late noble Lord, and
<pb facs="tcp:64837:4"/>Father, have been; we may earneſtly beg of God to add to Your Honour and Proſperity <hi>Fifteen Degrees,</hi> and prolong Your wonderful Life marvelouſly farther than <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s. If then You might ſee Your <hi>Sons</hi> not go backward in the World, but getting up (like the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> to the beſt and moſt difficult Advancements; I mean, up the many Steps to the <hi>Houſe of God,</hi> (there to praiſe his Bleſſings, and to pray for Yours.) I doubt not but it would be a Token of much Comfort and Honour to Your ſelf, and of as much Happineſs and Benefit to them, as to him, who is ready to ſay, (with the elder Brother, <hi>Gen. 27.31.</hi>) <hi>Ariſe, and taſt kindly of thy Son's Service, that thy Soul may bleſs me alſo.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64837:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LTHOUGH the Author's glorious Dedication of this Book <hi>(To the Queen of Heaven,)</hi> together with ſeveral other Reaſons, would have made me no more in love with this ſort of Complements, than the many are who have wrote long Diſcourſes againſt Prefaces, (and ſo have ſentenced themſelves with a Witneſs, by condemning the very Act in which they were found Guilty:) Yet finding by the ſad Example of moſt the Ingenious, who have failed in their attempts againſt Epiſtles prefatory (as he did, who deſigned a great Building without Inlets or Addreſſes to it,) that it is a hard matter for People to avoid the Road, and run over Hedge and Ditch, without being judged Men of odd Deſigns: I therefore take the beaten track to the Town, and am content to keep pace with anothers Motion; having took no courſe to appear before, nor being now ſpurr'd on to this Publication by any Sentiments, but thoſe of Gratitude before-mentioned. Were I ſtung by ſuch a Gad-fly as Vain-glory, I would not Print a Tranſlation now, (which was made above ten years ago) to dub me a Writer; when the Form of it, as much as the Matter, will be ſo dull and inſipid to the Wits of this time. (Theſe are for no Book-learning, no writing by Gentlemen, unleſs it be (at the Modiſh Rate) ſtrangely extravagant, profane, or foul.)</p>
            <p>Therefore as I leave theſe Gallants to the Tyranny of that <hi>Genius</hi> by which they both act and ſuffer; ſo purpoſely have I diſmounted their expectation of any paſs-time from me; for I have ſlipt the Spring, I have loſt the Seaſon for youthful Publications; and now I ſeek to have Audience <hi>incognito</hi> with a grave Senator.</p>
            <p>This, methinks, may be ſufficient Proof, that I neither qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, nor expect the ſtale Title of an Author, for all I am now like one in a Preface. Moſt Eyes are upon Books, as upon a Horſe-Race; on the firſt Start, or at the ending, more than upon the beſt part of the Heat.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, I tell the Readers what they may find here, though I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell what they may like; for if they look for much <hi>Roman</hi> Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, or <hi>Papal</hi> Devotion, they will go away unſatisfied: For I have
<pb facs="tcp:64837:5"/>changed the Religion, as much as the Language of my Author; and allowed my ſelf the ſame Chriſtian liberty in turning or trimming this Piece of his, which he likewiſe took in ſome of his Tranſlations: That as the <hi>Signor</hi> dreſſed it for his Country,<note place="margin">Vede loquinto Vol. del Sig. <hi>Gio. Fr. Lore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dano,</hi> nel prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatio ſua, All' Hiſtoria Catal.</note> I may look after it in mine, and bear the blame, if this Stranger be took for a <hi>Jeſuit.</hi> If I conceal ſome of his Expreſſions, 'tis not to abuſe his intent of appearing to the World a true Catholick; he is now, I truſt, Orthodox, and <hi>Engliſh</hi> too: Nor would I damp his Spiritual Heats, while I fan Superſtition from his great Ingenuity and Zeal.</p>
            <p>I know the Silk his words put on is pure <hi>Venetian,</hi> of too curious a Fabrick for me to mend, or indeed to meddle with farther than to add a Liſt of courſer Materials to the Piece.</p>
            <p>Leſt it ſhould ſeem too nice in its Addreſs to the holy Altars, and there be reproved (like an <hi>Agag</hi>) for its Delicacy, (falling under the Cenſures which many ſuch Works have incurr'd, of having more Wit than Zeal in it) and too much <hi>Rhetorick</hi> for much Religion) I have rebated the point of <hi>Loredano</hi>'s ſtile; and where I have cut off ſome reiterated Elegancies, and Muſical words, that (as long Fuges) were but to the ſame Tune; I took away the Lap of the Senator's Robe, I hope without doing him any injury at all.</p>
            <p>'Tis pity a rich Sleeve ſhould be ſo long, as to hang (like their <hi>Laticlavians</hi>) in the Dirt;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 25.23. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> or that <hi>Berenice</hi>'s appearance ſhould hinder <hi>Agrippa</hi>'s Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>I am more apt to exclude <hi>Tertullus,</hi> than St. <hi>Paul;</hi> and therefore, inſtead of <hi>Oratory,</hi> put in <hi>Scripture</hi> into the Work; that what is loſt in Fancy, may be retrieved in Devotion.</p>
            <p>And ſurely no time nor labour would be loſt, could I be but as much more uſeful to the Reader, as I ſhould be juſt to the Writer, in ſetting forth his Thoughts with the ſame pious Impreſſions and Advantages which they once brought to my Heart. To this they have done good, (as I may publickly own;) and I am not of ſo ſtrait, ſo narrow a Spirit, as not to endeavour to communicate a good, according to the Nature, and my Experience of it.</p>
            <p>Indeed before I travell'd into <hi>Italy,</hi> I heard ſo much ill ſaid of that Country, (eſpecially of the <hi>Venetians</hi> in it) that I was poſſeſſed with a prejudice like his,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 1.46.</note> who cryed, <hi>Can there any good come out of</hi> Galile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? And alſo prompted by the irreligion of too many Travellers, to think that Contagion the Epidemical Diſeaſe of Foreigners, (principally thoſe of higher Rank.)</p>
            <p>Therefore when I went abroad, leſt I ſhould learn Vices more faſt than Language, or live (as formerly) in the proud <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> conceit, that every Land was barbarous, but our own; and all the World was naught, but <hi>England.</hi> I was curious to find out what was Spiritual (and rightly ſo called) beyond Sea, if the lawful Iſſue of a Noble <hi>Laick;</hi> I look'd upon ſuch a piece of Devotion as more capable of doing good, than the more elaborate Volumes of Churchmen; (who are not thought well enough on, becauſe they make it their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to write well) whereas the ſlighter Eſſays of other Gentlemen (which are not of the long Robe) fall more gratefully into the hands of great Perſons, and by Emulation of the precedent (if no better motive) work often upon them ſome Pious effect.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64837:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Being acquainted with the Truth before-mentioned, and with the mighty number of <hi>Memoires,</hi> and other Works, lately put forth by the Noblemen of <hi>France,</hi> I ramaſs'd a good quantity of the moſt Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious modern Writers in <hi>Italy;</hi> and amongſt them, the firſt which I laid hold on, was the Third of the ſeven Volumes of the Honourable Signor <hi>Gio. Franceſco Loredano</hi>'s Works;<note place="margin">Stamp. à Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, <hi>1654.</hi>
               </note> which though ſet out with all the Garniſh that the Poets and Painters could enrich them with, yet diſcouraged my peruſal of them, becauſe I found the beginning of this Volume very Toyiſh and Romantic.</p>
            <p>'Till I conſider'd that Men's Books are oftentimes like their Lives; the firſt Parts of them ſlight and youthfull, (and ſuch Leaves as will ſcarce hide a Nakedneſs, nay, were better skipt over than peruſed;) yet their latter Ends may be Grave and Pious, well-order'd and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, as the Frize and Cornice of all their Works.</p>
            <p>So I ſearched on for the Pearl among the Shells; and left not this great and brisk Wit, 'till I found him terminate ſo well in Meditation, as that I fixed my hand upon his Table, thus to Copy out his Piety, if not his Eloquence; and to ſay (to thoſe who cried, <hi>Come from among them) Come and ſee, is not here a Prophet?</hi> Though he might have been formerly a <hi>Saul,</hi> he is now with the divineſt <hi>David;</hi> and this his propereſt Subject merited Diſcovery, though it lay hid, like <hi>Saul,</hi> in a heap of Stuff.</p>
            <p>Nor was I content only to open the Mine, or fetch out the Oar; but alſo to fine it from the Droſs; that this ſilken Ladder might be uſeful, where ſtronger (like the Bibles) were not ſo portable, for to raiſe or keep up ſome Devotion in me.</p>
            <p>And this, I thank God, it did, by my often looking on it; as <hi>La Scala Santa</hi> once had done too, when it happened to me at <hi>Rome,</hi> (as to St. <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Athens</hi>) that I had a good opportunity from an Idolatrous place, to pray with much Fervour and Charity for my ſelf, and all Men, that we might not be miſtaken, or Hypocritical, in our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippings of God, while with Pity I conſidered the Superſtitions of ſome Chriſtians there, who adored Stocks and Stones more than their Maker; and with ſhame thought upon the Prophaneneſs of others among Proteſtants, that would not allow God a peculiar manner, nor place of Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Thus have you the occaſion of the Title I give to this Book, and ſhall have ſomething concerning the Frontiſpiece.</p>
            <p>Though by the way take notice, that I was never a Promoter of Superſtitious Pilgrimages; nor ſo far reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as to follow her Steps farther than the Church of <hi>England</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves them: For all I have gone up the Stairs above-mentioned, and the Aſcents of <hi>Loredano</hi>'s Soul, I hope with ſome ſuch true Efforts as that Illuſtrios Senator deſign'd in his <hi>Preface,</hi> and endeavour'd in his <hi>Paraphraſe;</hi> to which good Act, this is but a Scene, or rather as the Curtain which may now be drawn away, leſt it hinder the Spectators better Objects.</p>
            <p>I have fancied the whole Piece to be a Sk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tch of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Viſion, and <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalter, like <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Scale, reaching to the Divine Throne, whereon devout Spirits have ſcope to run deſcant up and down, and by the various Motions of their Piety, (as by the ſeveral Degrees of their Underſtandings) they make better Muſic than the imagin'd
<pb facs="tcp:64837:6"/>Spheres could ever be ſuppoſed to do: For ſurely, thereupon is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the beſt Harmony of Heaven and Earth; and thereon we ſhall meet with a grateful Conſort, when we are left never ſo much alone by the World.</p>
            <p>For they who make no uſe of the Pſalms, nor Feaſt upon them by frequent Meditation, are as obnoxious to Errors, as I can be in any of theſe Thoughts. Therefore like a Travelling Pilgrim to Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> I purſue my Journey, hoping to reach the end of it, by doing ſome good to my ſelf, if not to others.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Jacob</hi> was required to make an Altar of thoſe Stones on which he reſted in his Journey (when he beheld Heaven's Eyes upon him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.1.</note> and Angels moving to and fro for his Succour;) ſo I thought my ſelf obliged to make an Offering to God,<note place="margin">2.</note> (as a grateful Monument) of that which had better'd me in my Progreſs, and help'd me to ſee who was with me in the way that I went;<note place="margin">3.</note> ſo as to bring me again to my Father's Houſe in peace.</p>
            <p>May then theſe Contemplations (and our whole Lives too) be like <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Ladder, ſcaling Heaven it ſelf; and having their higheſt ones there, (while ſome others may be yet upon the low Earth) and while good Thoughts and Actions (like Coeleſtial Miniſters) aſcend to Heaven, and condeſcend to Earth, let God be ſet at the end of all we do, that we may receive much Good from ſuch gracious Proſpects, and our Pillars (like <hi>Jacob</hi>'s) be Anointed to God's Service.</p>
            <p>For my part, I deſire to build no <hi>Babel,</hi> (of ſeveral Languages) but would bring ſome Materials unto <hi>Bethel;</hi> though the top of my perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance reach no farther than to lay the Foot-pace to God's Houſe.</p>
            <p>If <hi>David</hi> (ſuch a Maſter-builder) thought it Honour enough for him to be but as one of the <hi>Nethinim</hi> in the Temple; it will be more than Grace enough for me to be there (if but as a <hi>Gibeonite</hi>) in any degree ſerviceable to the Flames of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iety, or Wells of Salvation; while I officiate in both thoſe parts of Divine Worſhip, the two chief Duties of Religion, <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Thankſgiving.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſee the Soul hath ſeveral Steps to take, and many Rounds whereby to be exerciſed in her Addreſſes to God; and they are the Perches whereon ſhe can beſt recreate or reſt her State, while ſhe is in this Cage of the Body. Let us therefore make her as Muſical, and as Harmonious, as we may, therein.</p>
            <p>The very <hi>Pagan</hi> Worſhip was Spiritual enough to recommend Hymns and Singing to the Religious, (of what ſort ſoever they be;) and had I not mentioned far better Motives from Holy Scripture, I ſhould avow my ſelf conſtrained to this following Pſalmody, by the convincing words of ſeveral <hi>Heathens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionum Arrian. per tot. cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> ſuch as thoſe of <hi>Epictetus,</hi> cited by <hi>Arrian,</hi> and partly quoted in my Title-page.</p>
            <p>Nor am I diſcouraged in doing that, which others have done better before me; ſince I hear the Vertuous throughout every Age, as well as throughout the Bible, (like thoſe ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelations</hi>) ſinging in the words of the Princely Prophets, (<hi>David</hi> and <hi>Iſaiah</hi>) <hi>Come let us go up unto the Houſe of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.2, 3, 4, 5.</note> &amp;c. I was glad when they ſaid, not <hi>I'le,</hi> but <hi>Eamus, Let us go up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For though my Head or Hand be not publicly ingaged in the Service of God, or of my King; yet neither my Retreat nor Sloathfulneſs ſhall make me ſo bad a Servant, or a Subject, as not to employ my Pen
<pb facs="tcp:64837:6"/>and Ink, and Blood too, for Religion and Loyalty, as occaſion may be offered.</p>
            <p>At preſent, being happy in a long'd-for Receſs, I have the grateful Leiſure afforded me (which many good Perſons want, and might better improve) to thank God, that notwithſtanding our deſperate Provocations of him (which commenſurately heighten our Fears and Dangers) we are not yet ſunk down into that utter darkneſs of the days of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> when the ſaying, or ſinging of Pſalms, will be rejected with the Church. But we have liberty to go up, with <hi>David,</hi> into <hi>God's Houſe,</hi> and there ſtill beg thoſe ſureſt Mercies which are beſt for all Men, as well as for me, and ſo ſhould be deſired for us all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So be it.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64837:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64837:7"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>headpiece : portrait of Giovanni Francesco Loredano with coat of arms (repeated on subsequent pages)</figDesc>
                  <head>Joannes Franciscus Lauredamus</head>
                  <q>Lauredanus Laureandus</q>
                  <q>Facundus es. Clarus eris in annos</q>
               </figure>
THE AUTHOR'S EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT Pen which hath ſo often play'd the Fool upon the Stage of this vain World (by ſoothing moſt of the fantaſtic Humours, both of our own <hi>Genius,</hi> and of the Age) would gladly now take up, (like a redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Prodigal) ſtaying the Torrent of its wilder Courſes, that it might a while bemoan its Errors, and beg God's favour, and ſo raiſe its Plumes to a braver pitch; taking a glorious flight to the higheſt place of <hi>Paradice:</hi> For,</p>
            <p>The Glory of this World is raked up, or rather buried, in the Aſhes of our Humane Nature; and he is a mad Lover of Vain Glory, who is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender to Immortality, in a Place and Condition, where every thing is Mortal, like himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Here the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor reflects on his former Works, he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving writ many Volumes on the ſeveral Subjects here quoted, which have been moſt curiouſly ſet forth with ingenious Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſpieces and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendations.</note>But how ſhall we ſtir up, or awake the Divine Love, that we have either made ſad, and heavy, or made to reſt, and ceaſe, from doing us good, by a long Series of Offences? Alas! no Tales, or new Romances, dream'd by the finer Wits, to pleaſe or propagate the Ages Vanity; nor any ſerious Hiſtories drawn (like Minerals) out of dark Receſſes, by the Curioſity of their Undertakers, to profit and adorn Poſterity; no, nor any politic Maxims that dare teach the Art of Government to the Experience of mighty Princes, will now help us to work that Bleſſed Effect.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64837:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>It is needful to withdraw from the fruitleſs Works, from the hurtful Charms of vain Science and Verboſity; to avoid the Point and Praiſe of Men; to ſhun the Title and Eſteem of a Maſter in worldly Arts, and to run with devout Requeſts to intreat the offended Goodneſs, and loving Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our God.</p>
            <p>He continually bows down his Ear to ſuch Cries as (bringing with them the Repentance of the Heart) come in the ſtead of Holocauſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Heaven. Therefore that I might at laſt get thither, (though I have been long a Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor) I have walked up ſome Steps, (laid by the Royal Prophet) which may bring us ſafely to God's Houſe, and from thence to Eternal Felicities. And would to God my Heart could travel more with my Hand, that the Relliſhes of my Soul may be as devout, as thoſe of my Pen may ſeem! And that I had mounted theſe Degrees with ſuch purity of Affection, as this <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Ladder ſhould be raiſed, whoſe top reaches even to Heaven.</p>
            <p>So that whoſoever deſires to riſe to the moſt glorious Palace of the Son of God, if he would reach unto the ineffable Pleaſure of a Divine Viſion, he muſt walk up theſe fifteen Stairs which lead to Holineſs and Happineſs, and the main Induſtry labours in vain to get up to theſe, without Faith and good Works.</p>
            <p>Therefore I have here ſhewn (with <hi>David</hi>) that there are fifteen Degrees to the holy Mount, and high Place of Heaven; ſince to advance us thither are ſo requiſite, not only the eight Beatitudes, but the ſeven Gifts of the Holy Spirit: And he that in this Valley of Viſion knows not how to paſs on from ſtrength to ſtrength, will ſurely take the wrong way to <hi>Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are called <hi>Steps of Aſcent,</hi> becauſe who ever intends to make uſe of them, ſhould do it for his Advancement unto God; for his climbing up by Grace, and not ſuffer his humbleſt Thoughts to ſtoop ſo low, as to give any great Reſpect, or Entertainment, unto Earthly Objects.</p>
            <p>The five firſt Degrees are for Chriſtian Noviciats and Pupils, thoſe who begin their Journey towards Heaven in the way of Coeleſtial Love, and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to paſs through the difficulties of Temptation, the hardſhip of Affliction, the Swords and Pykes of Cenſure, and Calumniations. They are ſuch as (with <hi>David</hi> on his way to Victory) ſtay themſelves on their God, fix their Confidence (with <hi>Jacob</hi> in his Journey) upon Heavenly Succours, and rejoyce in Spiritual Supports, and preſs on forward in the hopes of Rewards; and in fine, have ſo much true Humility, as to attribute the ſmall Progreſs of their Repentance not at all to their own ſtrength, but wholly unto God.</p>
            <p>The five next Degrees aſſiſt Proficients in the ſame Love of God, and of Religion, who are forward in the way of Maſtering their Paſſions, and ſo are more confident, as better Confirmed, not only to further themſelves, but others too, in Divine Contemplations; as well as encourage and invite
<pb facs="tcp:64837:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to a <hi>Plus ultra,</hi> to a making on in the Love of God, 'till they have clearly made it out to themſelves.</p>
            <p>They can meekly beg of God a Confirmation of his Grace, and of their Strength; nor expect any reward, nor conceit any Merit, nor ſeek any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, either for the exerciſe of Patience in Adverſity, or for doing their Duty in that Condition wherein God hath placed them.</p>
            <p>The laſt five Degrees are for the higheſt Form of Profeſſors; ſuch as are neareſt the top of Perfecton above, and the Kingdom of Heaven here below; who can pray for their Perſecutors, do good to thoſe that do them hurt, and accompany their own tryed Patience with deſires of trying it ſtill more and more: Begging nothing more of God than Lowlineſs, and Nothingneſs of Spirit, under all the greateſt Demonſtrations of his Favour, leſt (with St. <hi>Paul</hi>) they ſhould be exalted above meaſure, and grow unworthy (by being Proud) of that Love, with which they long to be made one, in an Eternal Charity. Therefore taking their Hearts quite off from the World, and divorcing their Thoughts from Terrene Objects, they imploy their whole Man in beginning their Heaven upon Earth, by the continual bleſſing and praiſing of God.</p>
            <p>And I pray God theſe Words may be read with ſuch Thoughts, as may ſtir up each ſeveral ſort of Chriſtians to the devouteſt Action within their Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, kindling in every Breaſt one Spark or other more bright and fervent, than that can poſſibly be which is ſtruck out of the black Flint of my Heart, who (like <hi>Abſalom</hi>) have heaped up more Stones of Guilt for the Erection of a Monument in Hell, than I have enjoyed Hours of Life, for the ſteering my Courſe to the Glories of <hi>Paradiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Every Book that ſpeaks of God, ſhould be (as a <hi>Terminus,</hi> or Law-Stone) either to inform, or reform our Footſteps; and thoſe Columns are not (like <hi>Enoch</hi>'s) of Worth, nor of Duration, that build not up the Houſe of Wiſdom. Thoſe Figures ſtand but for Cyphers; thoſe Letters are but Mutes, that do not teach the Ignorant the Right way, or at leaſt, turn the Erronious from the Wrong.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs I acknowledge my ſelf not leſs unapt to Correct the one, than unable to Guide the other, being neither fit for the Office of a Monitor, nor of a Maſter.</p>
            <p>For what I have written, hath been rather to wake my own dying Devotion, than to watch for the Encomiums of others; and for once I can proteſt the Puff of worldly Applauſe, (which often Tympanies the ſoundeſt Minds with Ambition) did not blow up the Feathers of my Quill to this its preſent Flight and Undertaking.</p>
            <p>He that aſpires to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Honour (to talk with God as a Man ſpeaks with his Friend) doth not give heed to thoſe Whiſpers of the Serpent, to
<pb facs="tcp:64837:9"/>
thoſe vain Hopes, (I mean) which Fame and Reputation, thoſe <hi>(Terrae Filiae)</hi> Children of the Gyant, bring along with them to deceive us here.</p>
            <p>I once thought to be Dictator to my ſelf alone, becauſe Devotion is a Spirit, and like Camphire, if let out too far, or blown about, moſt commonly 'tis loſt, and vaniſhes away: But when I viewed <hi>David,</hi> (like <hi>Jonathan</hi>) climbing up the Rock, and commanding his Armour-bearers to follow him. I had alſo the courage, both to attend and imitate him, in beckening unto others to creep along with me upon theſe Stairs which lead unto <hi>David</hi>'s Fortreſs, unto the God of Gods in Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and unto his Temple, where every one muſt ſpeak of his Honour.</p>
            <p>And who knows but ſome others incited (perhaps by my weakeſt endeavours) may aſſiſt hereafter with better addreſs, thoſe who are getting up theſe Holy Rounds (this <hi>Scala Santa</hi>) of Meditation? As we ſee a little Star ſhines before the Sun, as it were to raiſe and light up a far greater and more uſeful Guide than it ſelf.</p>
            <p>But (without any more Preamble) not to detain, or deceive the Reader, let me tell him, who is not pleaſed with this Book, That he may be pleaſed in regarding the Subject; and if he ſhall look herein, and find any thing that is good, it is to be returned with due Intereſt of Praiſe to God, the true Owner of it, who was the Framer of the World from Nothing, and the Maker of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind Upright, though we have ſought out many ſtrange Inventions, both to be, and to do Wrong: So that Miſtakes, and Men, go hand in hand together; and all the Errors here we muſt yeild to be our own.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="song">
            <pb facs="tcp:64837:9"/>
            <head>IN Pſalmorum Laudem.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>CHORUS. 1. <hi>Angelorum,</hi> &amp;, 2. <hi>Hominum.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CHORUS.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>THE</hi> PSALMS <hi>are Paradiſes Spring;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Streaming Refreſhments every way.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They, 1. Wine, 2. Oyl, 1. Milk, 2. And Honey bring,</l>
               <l>1. To Cheer, 2. To Cure, 1. To Feed, 2. T' Allay.</l>
               <l>1. When we are merry, Pſalms we ſing,</l>
               <l>2. When we're afflicted, Pſalms we ſay.</l>
               <l>1. They Heav'n's, 2. And Earth's Devotions wing,</l>
               <l>1. While Angels Praiſe, 2. Or Men do Pray.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CHORUS.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> PSALMS <hi>are Paradiſes Spring,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Streaming Refreſhments every way,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:64837:10"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64837:10"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>decorative headpiece</figDesc>
               </figure>THE ASCENTS OF THE SOUL.</head>
            <div n="1 (120)" type="step__Psalm">
               <head>The firſt Step upon the Firſt PSALM of Degrees, being the 120 PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Ad Dominum cum tribularer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt Gracious God, when I have fathomed the toſſing Billows of my troubled Spirit, either by the depth of humane anxieties, or by ſome thwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting diſpenſation of that Providence that moves upon the great Abyſs: (and was termed Fortune, by the <hi>Heathens,</hi> rolling the whole Globe upon Waves of incertain Caſualties) Nay, when the Storms of my violent Paſſions make my wicked heart like a raging Sea (foaming out nothing but mire and dirt) in filthy Motions, and in tyrannical or rebellious Actions. O then, with Humility, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, and Sincerity of Intention, I indeavour to ſtrike ſayl, for fear of the Shipwrack of a good Conſcience, and make haſt to put into the Harbour of thy Goodneſs and Compaſſion. Then,</p>
               <p>I intreat that unſealed and unexhauſted Spring of Mercy, which (without upbraiding any for want of worthineſs) imparts to all of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64837:11"/>the fulneſs of his Grace. I have acceſs to thy Throne, O Father of Lights, and to Thee, O Glorious Sun of Righteouſneſs, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of perſons, haſt ſhined upon the juſt and the unjuſt, and lookeſt ſo kindly on the Univerſe, as to offer thy Beams and Beauties unto all.</p>
               <p>While on the other ſide, Thou merciful Lord (crowning thy Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Glories with the continued Acts of thy Pity) haſt ſo far leſſened thy Greatneſs, as to receive my Petitions, and not only heard my Prayers by thy Favour, but heap'd up Anſwers to them by thy Grace. So that my ever-craving needs have never wanted ſeaſonable ſupplies, nor my deſires wearied out thy Bounty: But every wiſh of mine hath worn ſome token of thy good will to Mankind, and every Prayer hath been returned (like an acceptable Meſſenger) with marks of favour.</p>
               <p>Seeing then I was made a Creature by thy Love at firſt, and a new Creation by thy Mercy now; I return again, O Father, with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal, to beg the exceſſes of thy Tenderneſs, the loud ſoundings of thy Bowels towards me; 'Tis more than ordinary preſerving or creating goodneſs that I want: And Thou, my Everlaſting God, haſt ever been my Saviour, ſo that to deny me now the continuance of thy Favour, or the bleſſing of thy Protection would be to looſe the fruit of thy Labour, and the end and Harveſt of thy former care.</p>
               <p>Therefore let thy Love be ſtill the Banner over me, while the Tongues of thoſe who are eloquent in fraud and falſhood ſtorm my Ears daily with Inveaglements, for the drawing my Heart off from paying its due homage of Thankfulneſs and Obedience to Thee, the Great and Almighty King.</p>
               <p>With the fears of thy Judgments they ſcare my remembrance of my faults, with the ſnares of their Allurements, they would draw me aſide out of the way that leads to Life; And with falſe Flatteries, they would indulge my compliance with Sin, and masking Vice under the ſhow of Virtue, ſeek to betray my ſoul, (that is too eaſie and pliable) to the Charmes of Senſe, and to the Pleaſures of the World.</p>
               <p>But alaſs! I perceive (though ſomewhat too late) how theſe Mouths of Hell, and Oracles of Satan would chriſtian Cruelty with the name of Juſtice, and name a curſed Revenge, the Way of Honour. With them, Covetouſneſs is but Frugality; Luxury, the Law of Nature; and Envy, noble Emulation. So that being well nigh loſt, and caſt away amongſt the dark miſts or falſe lights of their vain conceits, I find my ſelf deterr'd from good, and ſtay'd unhappily in evil.</p>
               <p>And truly, O moſt gracious God, without the aſſiſtance of thy Grace, and the protection of thy Love, without the buttreſs of thy Power, and the foundation of thy Wiſdom, What feeble <hi>Jericho's</hi> are all our Breaſts? How may the ſtrongeſt Walls of all our Virtues, and the higheſt Towers of noble Reſolutions be pull'd down (as it were with ridiculous Rams-horns) with the Breath of a naughty Woman, with the blaſt of an evil Tongue! And who is there (ſince <hi>Adam, Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Lot,</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> were blown down) that can avoid the faſcinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons either of flattery, or of falſehood of the Paraſite or Calumniator? Who can reſiſt the force, or withſtand the miſchief of ſuch inſnaring Words, as the Lyers Lips enter the Soul withal?</p>
               <p>The <hi>Syren's</hi> of the World, the <hi>Circe's</hi> of the Devil, and all the Idols of Senſuality may ſooner be paſs'd by, and more eaſily got from
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64837:11"/>by the exerciſe of Prudence, by the rules of Reaſon, and by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of Laws, than the ſnares that are laid by a deceitful wicked Mouth. And theſe are ſo much the more invincible and unavoidable, by how much they are inviſible and unknown, being ſpread over with the ſpecious pretences either of Piety, or of Friendſhip.</p>
               <p>The other miſchiefs of this frail ſtate here, may be grievous, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and mortal, but none ſo comparably to a falſe, malicious, and diſſembling Tongue, which is a painted Sepulchre, full of nothing but Emptineſs, Rottenneſs, Hollowneſs, and precipices inſtead of Amity, Righteouſneſs, Holineſs, and Piety, which it ſo much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to, as that it oftentimes intraps the moſt juſt and innocent, and tramples them under the feet of Calumny and Diſgrace.</p>
               <p>But O what fruit have you in thoſe things whereof you may be now aſhamed? O ye perfidious <hi>Doegs!</hi> What Pleaſure, what Profit, what Honour do ye gather from your Lyes, and from your falſhoods, O ye deceitful Men? Do ye Flatterers (who are the moſt venomous tame Beaſts) look for reward, or hope for praiſe, or expect immunities? No, no, your Company is too Pernicious, your Teeth too Poyſonous, your Sin too Preſumptuous, to expect any thing from Heaven but Hate and Vengeance.</p>
               <p>For the Javelin's darted from a ſtrong and ſteady arm gaſh not the Fleſh with deeper wounds than the Words of a treacherous and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Tongue pierce the Soul of the ingenious to the quick. The glow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Coals of Juniper, (which have the ſingular property of keeping Fire) do not reſerve, or afford ſo much heat as an evil Tongue can throw upon our affections, for that (ſaith the Apoſtle) is ſet on fire of Hell.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, my God, I truſt while thou doſt rain down Plagues upon ſuch ſacrilegious Sinners (as thou didſt upon <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> thou wilt preſerve my ſoul (as thou didſt righteous <hi>Lot's</hi>) that was vexed with the wicked Converſation of his Neighbours) ſo that I may not be overthrown amongſt the Pits of Diſſimulation, nor be ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack'd in thoſe unſtable Waters, where many a wiſe Pilot hath been caſt away.</p>
               <p>Lord! I would not run on the ſhelves of ſuch perſuaſions, as drive men on further to their own Ruin: But by the wonted effects of thy Omnipotence, deliver me from thoſe miſtruſts and miſunderſtandings that (too much indulging the impotence of Nature) take off the Man from doing his Devoir, and from obeying thy Commands, and ſtays him amongſt ſinful Complacencies and Delights.</p>
               <p>Againſt ſuch, O Lord, arm thy juſt wrath, and let thy diſdain ſtrike them on the Mouths, who full of miſchief and deceit become the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying places of others fame and reputation.</p>
               <p>O let the arrows of ſuch curſed Tongues, and the Goals of their traiterous Mouths, become Thunder-bolts to chaſtiſe their mallice; and lightning, to flaſh for ever in their Faces, and fire to puniſh their Offences everlaſtingly.</p>
               <p>And here now, Lord, the multitude of my Crimes committed at the inſtance of Sacrilegious Tongues, comes (with their Curſes) freſh into my mind. Here the remorſes of my Conſcience tell me of the Sins (and Plagues) I have contracted by my compliance with their vain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits (and company) who have too frequently taken me off from the performance of my Duty, and the obſervation of thy Holy Laws.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64837:12"/>Woe is me, wicked Wretch! O how weak! O how miſerable am I! Like the Prodigal, I have ſtay'd too long from home, from my Father's Manſion; from thy Love and Protection! And alaſs, How long have I ſtay'd in a ſtrange Land, and rebelled, like <hi>Abſalom,</hi> in the ſight of the Sun, before Heaven, and againſt Thee, O God! Declaring my ſelf no Son, that I might be a Slave to the Tyranny of my baſeſt Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and a Traitor to my Sovereign Lord! Surely, much too long and moſt unhappy hath been my Travel through this Wilderneſs, where I have made Woldly-mindedneſs my ſole Companion; ſo that I may ſay too too many, becauſe Evil have been the Days of my Pilgrimage.</p>
               <p>And ſurely, no greater mishap can befal a Man, than to find himſelf out-lawed from thy Care, and made a Vagabond, like <hi>Cain,</hi> in the Land of <hi>Aberrations,</hi> under the Rule of Evil Spirits, and among his own Deceivings and Temptations; ſuch evil Companions as may well be termed <hi>Arabians,</hi> from the Rudeneſs of their Behaviour, the Badneſs of their Neighbourhood, the darkneſs and deformity of their appearances, whereby (that Dove) the Soul, that is converſant amongſt them, is blacked and ſullied, as if ſhe had layen among the Pots, and loſt her ſilver Wings, and is by ſo much the more unpleaſant and unfit for the Eyes of thy Purity, by how much the more pains thou haſt took to make thy <hi>Pſyche</hi> without ſpot or blemiſh, or any ſuch thing, as the uglineſs of Vice diſguiſes the Soul withal.</p>
               <p>Free me therefore, O merciful Lord, from the iniquity and perverſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe Tongues that have not known the way of Peace, nor had they known it, would have loved it; becauſe, like the grand Enemy in the Goſpel, they are continually ſowing the Seeds of Hatred, and the Teeth of Diſcord.</p>
               <p>Nay, while they wear the Vizards of kindneſs and of peaceableneſs, they conſpire treacherouſly againſt the welfare of ſuch as would adore and ſerve Thee.</p>
               <p>Such Tongues, O God, flattering the ſenſual Appetite, ſubjugate Reaſon unto it, and make falſhood and blaſphemies ſo allyed to them, as that although they veil the miſchief of their deformities, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hide them. For, Can theſe <hi>Aethiopians</hi> change their Skins? No, they will appear the Black Sons of <hi>Cham,</hi> and like Leopards, full of Spots, let them daub over their Actions never ſo deceitfully.</p>
               <p>Lord, I wiſh that my Soul, being wholly devoted to Peace, may thereby join it ſelf to thy favour, and not ſtray at all from thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, but carefully trace thy divine Examples.</p>
               <p>O Bleſſed Jeſu! Thou haſt born ſo good a Will to Man, as to will Peace on Earth, as well as in Heaven, that Glory may be to God in the Higheſt. Thou didſt teach on the Mount, how that Hatred ſhould be baniſh'd, that Envy (not Juſtice) ſhould fly from Earth, and that Prayers ſhould be put up for all, even for our Perſecutors, and Kindneſs reſerved for our very Enemies.</p>
               <p>Thou gaveſt thy Apoſtles Peace for the beſt Preſent thou couldſt make them on Earth; Thou didſt leave them Peace for a Legacy, when thou wenteſt hence, and they ſhall receive from Thee everlaſting Peace for their felicity in Heaven.</p>
               <p>At thy Birth, the Angels were Heralds, who proclaimed a General Peace; And what did thy bitter Death bring, but the ſweeteſt pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation? As the firſt Words at thy Reſurrection were of Peace.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:64837:12"/>
               <p>But Gracious God, if thou delivereſt me not from that <hi>Iſhmaelite,</hi> (who purſues me with deadly hatred) and from his Children, who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him in Flatteries and Accuſations: I ſee, alaſs! the Repoſe of my Soul is ſo much broken by their Aſſaults, and its own Impotencies, as that it may deſpair of Safety. Becauſe, without Divine Aſſiſtance, no body can reſiſt the Witckcraft of thoſe Tongues, that are the Fire-brands of the Devil, and by his inſtigation, like the Fool in the Proverbs, throw about Fire and darts, and (as if in jeaſt) work nothing but miſchief and deceit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2 (121)" type="step__Psalm">
               <head>The ſecond Step upon the ſecond PSALM of Degrees, being the 121 PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Levavi Oculos.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>O My Soul! What doſt thou look at? What doſt thou look for? What doſt thou look after? Whence ſpring the Hopes which yield ſome eaſe to the Troubles and Evils of thy Condition? Who is he that can deliver thee from the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of Juſtice? Where wilt thou be ſecured from the Thunder of Divine Vengeance? See round about thee, nay within thee there are Ten thouſand Witneſſes (who are accuſers alſo) of the Exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances of thy Paſſion. Obſerve both by the late and ſad Chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of others (not ſo bad as thy ſelf) how ready the abuſed Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of the Almighty is to change it ſelf into Fury at thy continued provocations. Is not thy Conſcience gnawing thee like a Vulture? and ready to fly in thy very Face to reprehend the vanity of thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, the extravagance of thy Appetite, the blindneſs of thy Affection, and the infidelity of thy Opinions? Therefore gape no longer after the Tantalizing fruit of <hi>Sodom;</hi> ſtare not at the Tinſell Glories of this World; but lift up thy Spiritual Eyes in Love, and Prayer, and Contemplation, to the Rock of Ages, to the utmoſt bounds of the everlaſting Hills, to the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, thoſe Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of perfection who incloſe within the bowels of their Love all the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Holineſs, and the only means of our Salvation.</p>
               <p>Look up unto the top of this <hi>Piſgah</hi> and ſee all that bleſſed Land; ſee from this Summit how thoſe lower Heights who never feel the ſhowers of our Sorrows, nor fear the clouding of their Heads in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I mean the Beatified Saints and Angels (who have ſuch glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Elevations through the Magnetick force of God's goodneſs upon theirs) that like the Hill of the Lord they are venerably to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, and though thy weak ſight can reach no higher than theſe Hills, O learn from theſe thy Fellow-creatures the vaſt diſtance of thine own unworthineſs! when but compared even to them in whom thou haſt found Folly, and be confounded with Shame at thy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64837:13"/>far groſſer failings, ſo ſhalt thou learn to turn off the Thorns of the Fleſh, to turn out the Love of the World, and to turn away the Meſſengers of Satan.</p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt learn the right Methods of a ſincere and incorrupt Life, thou ſhalt learn to behold, and beholding admire that Hight of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that is above, and admiring thou ſhalt learn to get up to that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Company of Saints and Angels already gone to an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Paſſover before the Lord in his Holieſt Sion, and thou ſhalt not only have the Miniſtry of Angels but the help and protection of that great Angel of the Covenant the Holy <hi>Jeſus,</hi> to guid thee up ſafely unto thoſe who are gone before.</p>
               <p>But ſince, O moſt gracious God! the Aids which thy Creatures af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford are but inſtrumental and Miniſterial, without force or advantage, but by thy Will and Permiſſion.</p>
               <p>I therefore look from them unto Thee directly, having recourſe to thy Pity only, and imploring thy Aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Thou art my Creator, my Redeemer, my Comforter; my God and my Rock, if thou ſhouldſt reject my Supplications, to which of the Saints ſhould I turn to offer them up?</p>
               <p>If Thou ſhouldſt deny a Remedy for my weak Condition, from what Angel? or from what <hi>Betheſda</hi> could I hope for ſuccor?</p>
               <p>If Thou, who art the Fountain of goodneſs, ſhouldſt deny me to drink freely of the Waters of Life (for the reſtitution and repair of my Spiritual health) from what peculiar Stream or Ciſtern could one become ſo Loathſom and deſpicable, by reaſon of Infirmities, as I am, from whom, I ſay, could ſuch a one as I expect a draught, nay ſo little as a drop of Comfort?</p>
               <p>'Tis true Lord! my yielding to the guidance of a blind Leader hath ſubjected the liberty of my Will to the Tyranny of my Senſes, and Theſe adoring ſome weak and brittle reflexion of thy Lovelineſs, (in the fadeing beauty of ſome dying Objects) have made Earth my Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and ſo ingaged me amongſt worldly enjoyments, as to give me neither Liſt nor Leiſure to regard the delights above; but a Cloud of terrene ſatisfactions (which will ſoon vaniſh as a Miſt) have taken my <hi>Jeſus,</hi> my true Joy, out of my ſight: and I muſt confeſs, I have been leſs willing to look on the feaſting and refreſhing Veſſels of Heavenly Joys, than God hath been to prepare a Table, and to let down a Banquet for my Soul.</p>
               <p>O! how have I ſcornfully paſſed by, and turned my head away from the good <hi>Samaritan?</hi> When my Saviour hath bowed down his Head, even unto my Ear, and called upon me thus,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Is it nothing unto thee, O thou that paſſeſt by? Is it nothing that I have unbarred Heaven Gates for thee, and broken down the Gates of Hell? Behold and ſee quite through my Body, how the way to Paradiſe lies open to you: and ſince there are ſo many paſſages made thither for Sinners through my Wounds and Heart, why will you not believe that I am the Way.</q>
               </p>
               <p>O my dear God! I cannot excuſe either my neglects or infidelity; but I know our grievous offences do Crown the glorious Actings of thy goodneſs, and the innumerable Train of thoſe who are conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by thy clemencies do make ſuch ſplendid Triumphs in Heaven as thou moſt delighteſt in.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:64837:13"/>
               <p>The wondrous Frame and machine of the Heavens, the ſpacious Theatre of the Earth, with all the movements and ſpectators round about them, is the great Ball thou giveſt unto rational conſiderations, and was the work of thy Hands alone.</p>
               <p>Nothing it ſelf was matter enough for thy Omnipotency, from whence to build up the mighty Fabrick of the Univerſe. So that by the ſame power thou didſt Create, thou mayſt alſo Relieve and Redeem me from the Miſeries wherein I am plunged by my Sins.</p>
               <p>Without thy moſt Divine Aſſiſtance all my good intentions flagg and vary from the ſtrict obſervance of thy Commands. My Nature habituated and grown old in Evil, wanting thy help on every ſide, finds the Precipices of its endleſs Ruin. Thou only O my God! mayſt withold my falling, uphold my weak endeavours, and raiſe me out of the Gulphs of my Condition which is ſinking down to the lowermoſt Hell.</p>
               <p>Under the ſafeguard of thy friendly Aſpect mine Eyes fear not the blinding of themſelves on Sublunary Glories, my Tongue dares not Profane it ſelf with the vain diſcourſe of this looſe Age, my Feet will not follow the motions of the Fleſh, my Hands will find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves obliged to pious Actions, and my Ears will not admit of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſounds than ſuch as Eccho forth thy greatneſs and thy Glories.</p>
               <p>'Tis ſo indeed, moſt dear Redeemer! that under the Banner of thy Love I fear not the Forces of thoſe Enemies both to thy Croſs and to my Crowning, I am ſure the Captain of my Salvation will put to flight whole Armies of thoſe aliens of vain and intemperate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections who would Lord it over thine Inheritance, O Lord! and thou wilt heal my backſlidings ſo, as that Sin ſhall not be finiſhed to bring forth Death eternal.</p>
               <p>Comfort thy ſelf then O my Soul! that the care of God in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of men is ſo great as not to let him ſeem to ſlumber when thou haſt occaſion of thy Shepheards Staff; nor will he prove ſuch a ſtupid Patron as <hi>Baal</hi> did,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.27, 28.</note> when intreated by his Votaries.</p>
               <p>But if thy greater provocations hinder not his pity, this will ever be at hand to ſupport, to ſupply thy deficiency; and we have no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to doubt or deny the effects of his Vigilance who with ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied and conſtant attendance makes the Angels wait upon our Motions.</p>
               <p>Nay, although we leave, and tire God by our Sins; yet for all our wilfull Defections and Errors God hath never yet left or aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned us.</p>
               <p>This great Eye of the Univerſe is never cloſed, never blinded by our juglings, never impoſed upon by appearances, never heavy with Sleep; he decks the Glories of his goodneſs with the particular kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which he hath for the Sons of Men.</p>
               <p>If then the Majeſty of the moſt High not only by the Actings of his bounty, but by the Miniſtry of his Angels thus guards and governs, aids and accompanies frail Humanity; how comes it to paſs O my Soul! that thy Affections run from ſuch Fellowſhip, from ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to expoſe themſelves to the Shadows of Vanity, or the dangers of Senſuality?</p>
               <p>Why doſt thou venture thy ſelf ſo alone like <hi>Hagar</hi> in a barren Wilderneſs far from Heaven, from Angels, and from God, to ſeek
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64837:14"/>for Earthly ſatisfactions, or to let a ſervile corrupt Wilfulneſs do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineer over the?</p>
               <p>O reſiſt ſtoutly the aſſaults of the common Enemy, who (if it were poſſible) would allay the ſcorching of his own flames by throwing thee and other Souls into them. Therefore quench the violence of thoſe Tendencies that ſink thy Soul down from Heaven. Maſter the power of ſuch Affections, as deſpoiling thee of thy moſt noble part would cloath thee with the filthy Raggs of Sin: and then fear not Soul! for God is with thee.</p>
               <p>Indeed Lord, if my frailties did not rob me of the favour, thou ſhouldſt be my Maſter, teaching me the things which belong unto my peace, Thou ſhouldſt be my Guide, not only unto but through Paradice. Thou ſhouldſt be my ſafe Conuoy to defeat the Enemy of his rejoicing at my falls. Thou alſo ſhouldſt be my keeper to detourne me from the Snares which are daily ſpread for me by the pleaſures of Senſe: and I am weak (as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> once ſaid) Lord do thou undertake for me. Take upon thee my Guardianſhip and thou ſhalt ſee how valiantly I will reſiſt all the Temptations of the Devil. If thy moſt powerful Arm doſt ſhield my tender Heart, O Lord! what Power, though ever ſo inſolent, dares ſhoot an Arrow or throw a Dart againſt it? If thy Right-hand be my Support, what Force can over-turn me? Heaven hath no Thunder, Earth hath never a Mouth, nor Hell it ſelf an Abyſſe for ſuch as ſit under the ſhadow of the Almighty. When the great God ſets his Hand to the Charter of our Protection, or to the ſecuring of our ſafety, what alteration can all the changes of the World make on us? None, not any, <hi>Non ſi ruat Orbis:</hi> We cannot wander as e'rewhile from his mind, nor ſo groſsly tranſgeſs his Precepts.</p>
               <p>Rejoice then O my Soul! that God hath undertook thy defence by all his Divine care and induſtry, and hath made his Son a Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtage for our ſecurity, while he continually holds thee up by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched Arm of his Favour.</p>
               <p>O moſt Glorious God! it is thou alone that ruleſt all the Motions, the Ragings, the Madneſs of the World, and its Elements. Thou ſitteſt above the Heavens, (ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi>) thou preſideſt over all thy Works by thy Power and Mercy, ſo that thou canſt allay the force of every Influence in ſuch an Almighty ſort as that the Sun ſhall have no feavouriſh Darts, nor the Moon any malignant Aſpects to caſt on thoſe who are ſhielded by thy Protection.</p>
               <p>The Fire in its own quality is ſo violent and greedy, as never to ſay it hath enough, but after it hath devoured all in its way is ready to feed (like <hi>Envy</hi>) on it ſelf; how is it by the Heavenly Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence tempered in its unbridled Nature, and reſtrained from doing Miſchief, as held in from deſtroying both it ſelf and others?</p>
               <p>What ſhall I then ſay of thoſe Flames of ſenſuality, thoſe Fits of Intemperance, thoſe Epilepſies of Laſciviouſneſs, thoſe Rapes and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olences committed upon (and much againſt) our own Conſtitutions, which without a ſingular effect of Divine Clemency would ſoon tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and conſume our Nature.</p>
               <p>And who is there but ſome time or other plays the <hi>Curtius,</hi> and deſperately throws himſelf into the Gulph of Danger, rather than he will offer to turn the Stream of Pravity, which carries away our
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64837:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Affections ſo much the more precipitouſly and miſchievouſly, as we allow, it Natural and Born <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us. What force then O Lord! with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thy Sovereign help can bear the Shock of Ambition, or bridle the fury of Paſſions, or reſiſt the Aſſaults of Luſt? Thou alone, moſt Gracious God! mayeſt enlighten the blindneſs of my Mind, enable the weakneſs of my Heart, and invigorate the deſperate eſtate of my Soul.</p>
               <p>He that thinks to go out by himſelf in his own ſtrength alone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Uncircumciſed Enemies of our Peace, he knows not what he hath about him; how unprovided he is of Armour, and of Force to encounter ſuch Giants as may defeat him even by the falſeneſs of his own Nature. Man of himſelf being now ſo entangled, (in his own Land as it were) ſo hampered by his depraved and carnal Senſe, as that his very preſuming to fight his Adverſary with his own ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Weapons, is the ſhewing but of his Pride and Weakneſs, (the faults charged on <hi>David,</hi> and the Sins of <hi>Goliah</hi>) the defying of the Moſt High, and the diſgracing the Armies of the Living God.</p>
               <p>My ſafety therefore ſhall depend onely upon Gods defence, whoſe continual Guard and ſeaſonable Reliefs, free me from the injurious Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents happening in the Day or in the Night. So that all my time and life finds it ſelf exempt, or ſecured from ſuch continual Perils as are encountered in an Age ſo full of Sin and Violence, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo full of Miſeries as this Preſent is.</p>
               <p>O how doeſt thou diſarm the furiouſneſs of my Enemies, and of the whole Creation, Deareſt Lord? How doſt thou ſtop the Mouths of the fierceſt Monſters? (which are opened againſt Mankind ſince the Fall.) It is thou who doſt blunt the Cruelties of Thieves and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, and calmeſt the moſt violent Stormes, and humbleſt the moſt Lofty Pride. All Misfortunes, all Diſaſters, all Calamities are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by thy Power, and made beneficial to us by thy Providence.</p>
               <p>Continue therefore thy Favours towards my poor Soul, which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the weight of its Earthly-mindedneſs ſinks down into the Pit without the ſupport of thy Love. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rcover it as thou didſt <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s, and ſee how the Devil (that is ever imploying his uſual Malice) is allways in Ambuſh, or in open War againſt her. With the Complacencies of the Appetite he Charmes her, with the Heats of Ambition he Chafes her, with the Pleaſures of Senſe he Diverts, with the Snares of Beauty he Entraps, and with the Glories of the World he quite dazles me, frail Mortal, ſo that being near loſt and carried away by his cunning Deviſes (of which I would not be longer ignorant, O Lord!) I ſtruggle with the utmoſt effort to break away from the ſpecious promiſes and puiſſance of my Adverſary, that my Mind may not be debauched by the fair ſhews of the Fleſh, nor my Soul enſlaved to the unreaſonable paſſions of the Body: But that ſhe may fly to thy Aid, imploring thy Succor, and ſheltering me under the Wings of thy Protection.</p>
               <p>Surely, dear Lord! I have not tired out thy Pity, for all the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies of my Heart do want a continual Medicine; and un-interrupted applications of a Divine Hand; grant therefore O my God! through thine immediate Care and infinite Commiſeration the whole courſe of my Life may be ſo directed as that I may obſerve thy Commands, and the end of my Deſignes may be wholly thy Glory; the Scope of my Deſires, thy Service, and thy Love, the Center of my Affections.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:64837:15"/>
               <p>May the bright Emanations of thy Grace ſo ſhine upon my doings, as they having their beginning and end under thy Favour, nothing may draw me from thy Laws, or from my hopes of Happineſs.</p>
               <p>In a ſpecial manner do I begg thy Help O dear Redeemer! in that hour when the Man being attacqued with the Horrours of Death, grows faint and weary (like Thirſting <hi>Sampſon</hi>) and is in danger of quitting the Field to his greateſt Foes and moſt dangerous Aſſailants. In that blackeſt hour (which is the Power of Darkneſs) oh let me have thy cleareſt Guidance! O let me have that ſupernatural Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance which the moſt dreadful Conflicts do require.</p>
               <p>And now chear up my Soul with the aſſurance that thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended thy ſelf unto a faithful Creator, who will keep thee to the uttermoſt, and defend thy proceedings. He will not ſuffer thee to looſe the excellency of thy firſt being, nor to be always blurred with the Sordidneſs of Earth. He can Seal up all thy Faculties in the Contemplation of his Greatneſs, and having bleſſed the Periods of thy Life here, will promote thee to Glory in the Ages of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3 (122)" type="step__Psalm">
               <head>The third Step upon the Third PSALM of Degrees, being the 122 PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Laetatus ſum in his, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>O My God! what greater Conſolation can a Soul receive here than to be fed with the Hopes of enjoying thy Divine preſence hereafter? The Mirth of this World is ſo mixed, ſo daſhed with Vanity or Repentance, that 'tis no wayes comparable to what Eternal Beatitude can promiſe. Honours and Earthly Grandeurs are overloaded with the burthen of obſervances, diſſimulations and buſineſs, Worldly Riches are accompanyed with Labour, Snares, and Vexatious Conteſts. The delights of ſence are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed almoſt before injoyed, and of them nothing remains afterward but diſſatisfaction. All the goods of Nature or of Fortune are very fraile and momentary proving their felicities but vain and phantaſtick.</p>
               <p>But the injoyment of the Light of Gods Countenance, the introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the privy Chambers of Heaven which are hanged with Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and furniſhed with all real good is ſo great a favour, ſo ineſtimable a Jewel, ſo unparalell'd an advantage, as that the Soul it ſelf cannot comprehend much leſs the tongue expreſs it.</p>
               <p>How am I then arrived? O dear Redeemer! to a bleſſed pitch of Confidence by conſidering though I find my ſelf a very unworthy Sinner yet I may come (as I am call'd) into the Land of the living, into the Kingdom of Heaven, and when this Earthly Tabernacle ſhall be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64837:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>I ſhall have a Throne, a Seat, a Building not made with hands, Eternal in the Heavens.</p>
               <p>What greater happineſs? O my God! can a Soul promiſe it ſelf, then by ſeconding thy divine Commands, be ſecure of inheriting ſuch a Throne, ſuch a Seat, ſuch a Kingdom in the portion of the bleſſed? and in the preſence of Saints and Angels Communicate of thy own Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of thy Glory? What delights can equal thoſe of the Celeſtial Paradiſe? Speak no more of an Earthly one, for what ſatisfactions may keep pace with the Viſion of my God? (<hi>Adam</hi> himſelf could but view his works in the Univerſe.) But,</p>
               <p>O thou great Ineffable, Incomprehenſible, Tranſcendent! Wilt thou ever become the Object of thoſe Eyes that have been prophaned by Worldly Spectacles? In thy preſence is Life, full Content, and endleſs Joys, and theſe I ſhall as fully poſſeſs, (being inſtated by thy Favour) as Angels or other perfect Spirits have them, ſo my deſires ſhall be ſtill feaſted with the Contemplation of thy Goodneſs, and my affections ſhall triumph in their eternal injoyments and the inſatiable Nature of my Soul and ſence will find enough to entertain and quiet them in the infinite Treaſure of thy Love and Wiſdom.</p>
               <p>But becauſe he deſerves no admiſſion into the Cloſſets of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous who hath made his abode amongſt the Carnalities of the World and inſlaved his reaſon to the ſervice of ſin. <q>I pray thee moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God, to ſtay the feet of my longings from going up too haſtily, too raſhly: Hold my thoughts yet longer upon the Reflection of my own demerits, and then afterward fix them on the ſole contemplation of Heavenly things, ſo I ſhall better find the Obligation I have to ſerve thee with pure intentions, and ſuitable operations and not continue ſtill only fit to be ſhut out of the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that is above.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> I mean whoſe walls are built up of ſeveral orders of Vertues, whoſe ſtately Pallaces are reared by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Revelations of the Prophets, and the labours of the Apoſtles, the ſufferings and Patience of Saints, and the power of the Goſpel, wherein the glorious Majeſty of Chriſt Reſides, and the beſt Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are ſet off with Love and Charity, and the Angels are the bright Courtiers; Thrones, Dominions and Powers, chief Officers, Arch-Angels the Guards, and the bleſt inhabitants are the juſt made perfect.</p>
               <p>What then ſhould a man do? or rather what ſhould he not do or ſuffer, to get to this <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> above? O my Soul! thou muſt know that Heaven is a free and General native Countrey, that is arrived at not by nobleneſs of Birth, nor by the pride of Life or living, not by the glories of Anceſtors, nor by the Wealth nor Honours of the Earth, but by the Holineſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acts of our deſires, the ſincerity of the Heart, the temperance of the Tongue, and the Righteouſneſs of our Actions.</p>
               <p>Here then my Soul fix all thy Complacencies; thou haſt already cloy'd thy apetite on the momentary pleaſures of a ſhort Life, and thou findeſt how brief they are in the fruition, how bitter in the recanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them.</p>
               <p>Get up therefore, get up to this new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which the pity and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my God doth promiſe thee, while by his infinite Mercies he lets thee taſt the fruit of his planting, the wonderful Conjunctions of Faith and eternal Glories, and will let thee partake of the chief good (that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon portion of ſuch as are found worthy to be called the children of God.)</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:64837:16"/>
               <p>Haſt thou no reaſon then, O Soul! to give thy ſelf up abſolutely to the goodneſs of my God? what ſhould hinder or impeach thy ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion? is not this due to the merits of his goodneſs and to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merits of thy former Operations? Yea ſurely by ſo much the more art thou oblig'd to his ſervice, by how much the more his bounties have been extended towards thee. Therefore after all this his payment of thy debt of tranſgreſſions, I find thee bound more faſt to thy debt of Duty, to fear Gods Power, to adore his Majeſty, to be humbled for my Pride, and aſhamed of my follies.</p>
               <p>Heaven is no place thou knoweſt for the unclean, there are none but Innocents or Penitents, ſuch as have needed no Repentance or elſe have uſed it.</p>
               <p>O thou moſt gracious Monarch of the World! whoſoever pretends to aproach thy Throne, to partake of thy Glories, or to enter into thy garden of Life: He muſt of neceſſity be inſtalled with the Veſture of thy Grace and be ſtript of all Earthly compliances which ſo intangle men amongſt the ſnares of Offences or the miſeries of this Life.</p>
               <p>All they who to this time have ſtay'd in the Preſence-chamber of the Heav'n of Heavens, have been ſignalized with the ſpecial characters of thy Love (without which all our indeavours are alike Blind and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,) they alone have gained that place and honour, by the ſincerity of their Conſciences, by the purity of their Lives, by the cleanneſs of their hands in thy ſight O Lord, as ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let this be owned by (thoſe Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> thoſe choſen people and that Royal Prieſthood of Thine,) who being advanced to an heavenly height by the ſteps of their Vertues, have made thy greatneſs (conjoyn'd with thy goodneſs) to be Ecchoed through the Univerſe, to the ſhame and confuſion of others more oblig'd who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they be inriched by millions of Benefits yet know not how to reſpect the Donor, acknowledg the Gift, or ſanctifie thy Holy name therewithall.</p>
               <p>Lord I am ſenſible of the backwardneſs of my Heart to any grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, it is conſcious of it's own Guilt, and would not go no farther till it hath confeſt, how the obſervation of thy Commands hath been the leaſt of its care, and thy Love, (which ought to have been the firſt deſire of my Heart) hath by my ignorance been ſo neglected, as that the fading ſparks of a beautiful look have more eaſily inflamed it then thy preſence.</p>
               <p>As many Objects as have been offered to my ſenſe, became ſo many Idols, to the which my paſſions were devoted.</p>
               <p>Thy divineſt Name hath been caſt out of my Mouth in a Thouſand vain aſſeverations, and theſe have been uttered to no other end, then to give Credence to the vanity of my intentions, or the falſehood of my Speeches. How then, can theſe Eyes, theſe Ears, theſe Hands, theſe words of mine, plead themſelves guiltleſs of any Crime? ſince they have or would have offended in all, and this conviction of my own guilt, frights me with the thoughts of thy comeing with thy Holy ones to judge the World, leſt I be then found in the number of ſuch profane wretches as ſhall be ſhut forth of thy Caeleſtial Manſions.</p>
               <p>I therefore dread that laſt and great Aſſizes of thy Saints, moſt glorious God I fear that general Summons, and the Aſſembly of thy firſt born, leaſt when that Bench ſits upon the examination of my
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64837:16"/>Actions and Omiſſions, how I have neglected the directions of their Doctrine, and not imitated the goodneſs of their Manners, nor traced the footſteps of their Charity, nor admired the proofs of their Patience: <q>I being ſo vile a ſinner, (ſuch reprobate ſilver) may be rejected, for if I am apprehended without the wedding garment of Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; I have nothing to ſay for my ſelf, no plea to make, ſaving the inexpreſſible deſire of my poor Soul, not to be excluded with Doggs, but to enter into the Holyeſt City the new <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I confeſs good Lord, that I have neither worth nor will, to follow the conducts of thy grace, nor to arrive at thy Favour: all the courſes of my Life have been great aggravations of my guiltineſs, for I have ſlighted thy Omnipotency, by prideing my ſelf in thy extraordinary gifts. The very ſight and heat of the Sun have appeared, not the Loanes of thy peculiar bounty but things made on purpoſe for my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience.</p>
               <p>The return and pleaſure of each ſeaſon, hath been reckon'd the unavoidable actings of ſublunary Creatures. Thunder, Lightning, and ſtorms of Hail, were too often counted the neceſſary effects of ſecond cauſes. Thus Brutiſh have I been, thus blind and yet I knew full well there would not be a Breath of Air, nor ſo much as a leaſe wag un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it were by thy appointment, that makes every Creature live and move and have a Being.</p>
               <p>Yet alaſs, for all I can ſo ſpeciouſly declare this, I muſt confeſs alſo that many a time when my tongue undertook to diſcloſe thy Name, with the due Attributes of thy greatneſs; my wild heart hath then witheld its aſſent, and been ready to give the lye to my ſpeech.</p>
               <p>Since therefore all that I can ſay of my ſelf ſpeaks me very guilty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee O Lord, I Plead, not any Merits but thoſe of my Saviours Paſſions, not any goodneſs but that of thy Divine Nature; afford me theſe, through thy Grace, and then I ſhall have that peace (which is an inſeparable accident to it) I ſhall have ſuch a Magazine of bleſſing as may render my Soul like a ſtrong fortreſs, well provided againſt the aſſaults of the World, and the ſnares of the Devil.</p>
               <p>Gratious Lord! I have often begg'd the favour of thy mercy to draw me out of that wretched ſtate of my prevarications, and from the ſlavery of Concupiſence, and from the Tyranny of evil habits, I know how weak, how blind, how falſe or infirme, our own Nature finds it ſelf at the beſt, and therefore he that ſuppoſeth (without the aſſiſtance of thy goodneſs, without the armour of thy Grace, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the incouragement of thy Love,) either to quell the impetuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Luſts, or to get up to the holy Hill, deſtroying like a <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan</hi> all his enemies in his way, ſuch a one muſt ſurely be more then a Man, or miſtakes himſelf groſly; for he ſhould know 'tis only from the exceſs of thy pitty, that a ſinner is turned from the evil of his way.</p>
               <p>The prodigal ſoul that hath long ſtrayed, can never make up its loſſes nor mend its condition, unleſs it be by the inexhauſted treaſures of thy Grace.</p>
               <p>Help me therefore, and redeem me from the power of Satan unto God, that being intruſted with thy Talents I may ſhew forth to all thy manifold goodneſs, and tender Bowels of Compaſſions ſo that ſinners (many with my ſelf) may be farther converted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Thee, and by my example inflamed with thy Love, renounce
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64837:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>Earthly Toyes and pay thy Clemency the due Tribute of penitential Tears.</p>
               <p>And from whence dear God! art yet more glorified then by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving us poor ſinners? Thy mercies are likewiſe a guide for ours, ſince all the Acts of thy goodneſs and kindneſs, may in ſome degree be imitated by man. He was formed after thy Image, and the more juſt and holy he is, the more doth he approach unto Thee. That Prince who beſt reſembles God on Earth, muſt own his power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or to puniſh from thy ſpecial grant O Jeſu.</p>
               <p>The Martyrs have eſſayed to copy out thy patience, the Virgins thy purity, Confeſſors thy truth, and Hermits thy Innocence. <q>But alaſs! How far ſhort are they of the Original? They have repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented thy image as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks but as in a glaſs very darkly, and deficiently. For as the Heavens are higher then the Earth ſo far more excellent are thy operations and affections then ours,</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The proofes of thy goodneſs are infintly Tranſcendent and inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible, rather to be admired then exemplifyed, and did not all the Prerogatives of Heaven and Earth, concur to ſet forth thy greatneſs and to ſpeak thee the Lord of Hoſts: Yet thy goodneſs alone would deſcribe thee moſt admirably according as thou declaredſt thy ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Lord, the Lord merciful and gracious, ſlow to anger and abundant in truth and goodneſs.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore extend theſe glorious attributes towards my relief, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance thy lovely Titles, by the forgiveneſs of my ſins, I have no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe to urge, but that by how much the more unworthy my Soul is of pardon, by ſo much the more will thy pity be ador'd in the pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4 (123)" type="step__Psalm">
               <head>The fourth Step on the fourth PSALM of Degrees, being the 123 PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Ad te Levavi, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>COme Lord! O come and and help my ſinking Soul, that being ſear'd with many troubleſom Illuſions, will let me fall (I doubt) into the dark of ſin, I have experienced to my coſt how much the ill propenſities of my Nature corrupt my ſentiments, and habituating me to the reliſh of tentation, almoſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me 'tis impoſſible to reſiſt.</p>
               <p>I live indeed with my ſelf, far from my ſelf, at ſuch a diſtance from a good mind, as to be without the neighbourhood or acquaintance of my own bad one.</p>
               <p>Self love deludes me with falſe reflexes and gives to vice it ſelf the ſurname of Vertue, it makes me a ſelf-deceiver and a groſs flatterer of my own opinions, ſo that I am apt to ſpare and connive at my ſelf
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64837:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the midſt of my greateſt delinquencies; but not to entertain my ſelf any longer among the miſeries I contract, nor to caſt away my life too blindly amongſt errors. I lift up the Eyes of my Soul to the light of thy divine Preſence, and with a ſteady Faith, a lively Hope, a moſt ardent Love, a fixed Contemplation, a ſtrong Patience, and a ſincere Indeavour, I implore thy Aſſiſtance, and intreat thy Mercy.</p>
               <p>My ſight hath loſt its ability in regarding worldly Objects, and I would not injoy any other Viſive faculty, but that which thy wonderful grace may afford me, let him aim and look at dirt, who full of earthly deſigns waits for all his comforts here below, I who for my part ſtore my chiefeſt Treaſure of bliſs and ſolace in a Heav'n above, turn all my thoughts and my affections towards thee, who art my only Lord and Maſter; I have ventured again to lift up theſe two doores of mine eyes, theſe humble gates of viſion, even to the lofty Throne of thy Majeſty, and my deſires have made bold to enter like <hi>Eſther</hi> unto <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes,</hi> even into the Cabinet of thy graces and glories; unto the boſome of thy Love Chriſt Jeſus, and they have found admittance hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto by the confidence thy goodneſs, and pity doth afford Them in a Saviour.</p>
               <p>I acknowledg my ſelf like an humble ſlave that waits for pardon of his faults, Relief of his neceſſities, protection from injuries, freedom from his chains, deliverance from further perſecutions, in a word I expect through thee my dear Redeemer Jeſus whatſoever may advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage my outward man, or felicitate my inward. I am not for retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any farther from thy preſence like a guilty <hi>Cain,</hi> ſince it is by the light of thy countenance, by the favour of thy grace, that I would chaſe away the thick clouds of my ſins, and never more looſe the light of thee, my Father which art in Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Thou art the Chariot of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and the horſemen thereof, the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thee far away from us is the fooliſh and deſperate attempt of looſing God, of looſing his favour indeed as <hi>Jonas</hi> once did to meet with what is monſtrouſly Horrid, but not of getting out of thy ſight (as that Prophet did experiment) for though we goe down into Hell: There art Thou alſo and thine eye can reach us.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore will I keep mine eye fixed on thee: O thou Father and fountain of Lights! and will fear to fall under any ſuch eclipſes as thy diſpleaſure, or my tranſgreſſions may bring upon me. I was once ſo hoodwinckt by the pleaſures of ſin, as to be led about fondly by the falſe glitterings of the World, I have been dazled by a frail Womans beauty ſo as to think there hath been no Heaven like a kind look from her, nor have I look'd at any other happineſs, then hath ſhone from from her eyes, which were two wandering ſtars alaſs, which in a little ſpace of time muſt ſet without hopes of ſhineing out again.</p>
               <p>My blind ambition carried me no farther then mortals praiſes and my deſigns ſmelt of the ground from whence they ſprang, my paſſions grew not feebler while my perſon did but waxed more robuſt as I grew older, and when I became nearer to my end (and had leſs need of worldly entertainments ſuch as wealth and honour,) then I became more greedy after them.</p>
               <p>How baſe is that mental Idolatry inſlaves us to the worſhip of that which hath it ſelf no more value then is given by the opinion of ſome fooliſh adorers? and as the femal graces of ſhape or complexion come
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64837:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>as it were by accident, ſo theſe are ſubject to ten Thouſand caſualties from them, neither gave theſe to themſelves, nor can keep them, (unleſs by great deceipt and Colour.) I now ſee what phantaſmes all thoſe honours are, which are ſought with great pain, poſſeſſ'd with fear, and loſt again with torment.</p>
               <p>Therefore deareſt God! I am returning to thee and leaving worldly pomps and paſſions, to thee alone addreſs my prayers, my deſires and my vows. I will be like thoſe Domeſticks, who ſerve faithfully and and ſeek Diligently to pleaſe their Lord, by minding his buſineſs, and his beck, that they may pleaſe and profit him to the utmoſt.</p>
               <p>I will attend with longing eyes for thy favour and pardon, and look to thy mercy ſeat, while I caſt not a glance upon the glories of the world (as I have done,<note place="margin">Pſalm <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> that Baſilisk ſhall no more inven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome my life by its regards, but ſhall be trampled under the feet of my contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; luxury, and vain glory, ſhall be trod down into the duſt as low as Humility can lay them or me; and the richeſt intrals of both Indies ſhall have no treaſures big enough to bribe my deſires from the ſervice of thy Heavenly Majeſty.</p>
               <p>Have mercy then, O gracious Lord! have mercy on thy poor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted ſteward, and deliver me from the evil of this defect and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, both from ſin and ſuffering by grace and glory.</p>
               <p>If thou doſt not by the tranſcendencies of thy power and goodneſs, free me from the miſeries of my guilt, and reſtore me to ſome degree of pardon (which is Innocence in thy ſight) where can I firm my hopes, from whom can I expect Salvation?</p>
               <p>I was form'd according to thy Image, imbelliſhed with thy reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance in a ſuperfluity of ſpiritual and temporal indowments, and yet I could not for all this preſerve my ſelfe in a ſtate of purity or ſafety: So that without the renew'd favours of thy goodneſs, I might expect no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but thunders and lightnings from the Throne, and flaſhes from the lake that burns for ever. Without thy Aſſiſtance O my God! I am affraid of thy foregoing promiſes, that I ſhall not be able to keep my word with thee, nor keep my heart from worldly luſts, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I have ſound my ſpirit running out of it ſelf too often, into the Arms of ſin and miſchief; frail humane nature being utterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled from maintaining thy favour, without thy overruleing grace.</p>
               <p>I am not a little ſenſible of the impotent commotions of my Soul, and the frequent domineering of my paſſions, ſometimes Ambition drives me after the ſeeking a trouble (which our ignorance calls a Title) of Honour. Somtimes I am wrackt with ſuſpicion of diſgrace, or I hunt after reputation by any means but by godlineſs. Now I am affraid of dying, or of leaving that to the earth which was borrowed of her for me: anon I am vex'd in the poſſeſſion or acqueſt of Riches which ſome call felicities, others find to be torments, and then complain of any ſlight miſchance as if theſe happened without thy providence, or were not produced by my demerits.</p>
               <p>Thus my ſtate doth ſufficiently experience, each exceſs of humane wretchedneſs by the agitation of my faculties to my diſturbance or danger, nor without thy help and mercy, Lord can I find how to get out of this wretched condition, nor how to keep my ſelf well if I were out.</p>
               <p>My weak ſhoulders ſtoop under the weight of thy commands as if
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64837:18"/>theſe were like my ſins too heavy for me to bear; and my corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons exhale matter continually to croſs my reſolutions, of not offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee.</p>
               <p>Stay therefore O Lord, and take the ſword of thy Spirit, and ſtop the way for me. Stetch forth thy hand above the fury of mine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, and ſhield me with thine arm againſt them.</p>
               <p>Let not the fiery darts of my Concupiſcenſes divert or prevent thy bounties or turn thy patience into diſpleaſure. For (as I have ſaid before) I muſt again acknowledg, that (without thy continual aid) I ſhall become a prey to their force and malice who (to the diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy power) would in ſpight of it ſubdue and inſlave me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5 (124)" type="step__Psalm">
               <head>The Fifth Step on the Fifth PSALM of Degrees, being the 124 PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Niſi quia Dominus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IF in defence of my known weakneſs, thy power O God! were not provided with a like infinity of commiſeration; and if this did not ſeaſonably come in to my relief, how ſhould I Stem the tide of Paſſions which dangerouſly ſwells up my breaſt? what would become of me in ſuch a deluge as they would throw upon me? Ah! let the pureſt Soul confeſs, and the choiſeſt Spirits acknowledg together with the Elect and confirmed Angels: that if the Holyneſs of a Saviour had not ſhelter'd theirs; if Jeſus had not bid the Waves and Winds be quiet and obey him; who of them all might not have ſunk down and periſhed in the ſtormy Lake? Had not Chriſt halcyon'd the proud ſtorms of our Paſſions, had he not quel'd the miſeries of this life, who could have born them? who amongſt us could have rid ſafe through ſuch tempeſts? or have held out againſt ſuch attacks as the ſin beleaguer'd Soul incounters? None could have promiſed eaſe or a ſanctuary to our vex'd minds, none could have reach'd to the ſerenities of Heaven.</p>
               <p>Our ſtrength is weakneſs (ſay the Scriptures) if not ſtrengthn'd by divine ſupplies. The Mettal, or condition of our humanity is too brittle to be truſted, if not back'd by the author of our Salvation.</p>
               <p>Keep therefore with my heart continually O God! that the Image of thy Son may not fall in darkneſs or in the ſhadow of death, nor that ſoul be loſt for which he took to himſelf a body.</p>
               <p>If I have not thine ayd O Lord! I cannot get out of the dungeon of my ſins, nor avoyd the ſtings of that infernal ſcorpion, but thou without looking on the demerit of my crimes, and the tranſgreſſions of my paſt life, wilt I hope aſſiſt and deliver me from the perills both of ſoul and body, wherewith I may be ſurrounded.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:64837:19"/>
               <p>I am ready to cry out who is ſufficient for theſe things? How can I reſiſt the attempts of the fleſh, the allurements of the world, or the aſſaults of our cunning adverſary the devil? I am intangled as the unhappy <hi>Laocoon</hi> is ſaid to be.<note place="margin">Aenoid. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>When three ſuch poyſonous ſerpents, crawling out of the earth are twiſted againſt me: They make ſure of my ruine; and how can I break the knots of ſuch a triple League? ſince the beauty but of one face (adorned with ſeveral charms) had almoſt got the command of my heart? and the ſolace of idleneſs, the ſweets of riches, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of vain glory many times captive my affections ere I am aware of them, what may not the cunning therefore of the Father of theſe falſhoods impoſe upon me, ſince he differs not in power from the beſt of the Angels, but in the manner of his operations, if not reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by thine immediate hand?</p>
               <p>When ſuch dangerous enemies had attacqued my inconſideratneſs, and batter'd my cowardice, I having but little or no conſtancy nor integrity, I had certainly become the prey of their malice, and they muſt needs have left me in the very jaws of death and damnation.</p>
               <p>Away then from me all ye inſtruments of ſin and miſchief above named, goe ye buiſy ſeducers of the beſt mens ways, <q>Ye with your jugglings dazle the eyes of the Soul, that like a Sodomite it ſhould not find the Dore of Life,</q> the way to get into the City of the Lamb, ye ſo varniſh over the Copy of Falſhood, as it proves a hard matter to diſcern her from the Original of truth; and our Conſciences are hurt (not purg'd) by your ſugaring over the draught of Sin.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, O merciful God! let that invincible power by which Lucifer was tumbled down from Heaven, and Hell it ſelf led Captive, free me from theſe Hunters after my Life, theſe noiſom Peſtilences to my Health, theſe tyrannick <hi>Nimrods</hi> againſt my Liberty; if their malice be once turned into fury what ſhall I do? for if thou hadſt not been my Refuge and Fortreſs I had fallen through that baſeneſs of Mind which is incident to the Sinner, who doubts of finding any Friend in his own Heart, or any Evidence in his Conſcience, but what will be againſt himſelf. If thou hadſt not by thy unſpeakable bounty afforded me ſome patience and perſeverance to diſentangle me from many wicked devices, perhaps the Waves of my Afflictions and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls would have ſwallowed up all the Faculties of my Soul, and made my Heart a Cage of unclean Birds, a Veſſel full of nothing but what was foul and beſtial.</p>
               <p>But by thy aid I muſt acknowledge it is that I have given place to Charity and Forgiveneſs (without regarding the nice punctilioes of the blinded World) then when Egg'd on by the deſire of Revenge, (which is the keeneſt Goad in the ſides of Fleſh and Blood) I ſtrove to ſet up my ſelf far above my ſelf even in thy Throne of Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. But,</p>
               <p>For all I might have once too vainly thought to ſecure the beſt ſhare of thy favour, when I made a Covenant with my Eyes (which are as Tinder to the Fire of Amorous paſſions) not to ſtoop at any Femal Object: and when I farther attempted to ſet up the Government of Reaſon over all the mutinies of my ſenſe, and ſo to get a Triumphal-Wreath by the paſſing ſafely through thoſe dangers
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64837:19"/>which threatned to overwhelm my Soul. O Lord! I find now that I Deſigned too much; Doing ſo little and Conſidering leſs; that without thy gracious and continual Aſſiſtance, without the extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt Acts of thy bounty my utmoſt endeavours had been but Flouriſhes in the Aire, and Paeans before a Victory. <q>They might have allarmed my Adverſary, awaked his greater force and policies. But the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaping his malicious devices would have been without the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of my Power and Arms.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>When I perceived this, I could diſcover alſo that it was thy good will I ſhould gain a Conqueſt, and though my ſtrength was but weakneſs, yet that this my weakneſs ſhould not be wrought upon too far by all the force and cunning of my Adverſaries.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore gracious Lord! I pray, that thy Goodneſs may have its due praiſe, that thy Mercy be greatly bleſſed, and thy Greatneſs glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified; ſince thou haſt not ſuffered my viſible or inviſible Foes to triumph over me, but thou haſt delivered me (like <hi>Daniel</hi> from the jaws of thoſe <hi>Abaddons</hi>) who would have torn and miſerably deſtroyed, even my better part, my Soul.</p>
               <p>O that I could immortalize my Voice to reſound thy Name more Gloriouſly! O that all my Words might become Spirits, and that I could devote them all to the ſervice of my God, as a ſmall acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of the grace received from thee!</p>
               <p>However I fall ſhort I will endeavour to ſpeak my ſelf not inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible though unworthy of thy Favours. I will try if my Arms (who have hitherto ſerved as Chains to embrace the Debauches of the World) may be turned into Columns erected unto Heaven in Thankſgiving and ſupplications for thy help. I will try if my Mouth (which hath been the Gate of Dishoneſty) may become a Theatre echoing forth thy Praiſe, as in thy holy Temple. I will ſtrive to fit up my Heart into a Lamp for thine Altar, where it ſhould be ſtill flaming with a Zeal for thy Glory.</p>
               <p>It hath been a Veſſel foully ſavouring of the ſmutty affections of Earth, but I hope to cleanſe it from ſuch taints, now that I may liken my Soul to a Bird, which hath broken through the Snares of the Fowler.</p>
               <p>Thanks to thy Pity gracious Lord! I now find the Devil was not ſo skilfull in laying his Snares, as thy Wiſdom hath been in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat of his Stratagems. He like <hi>Nimrod</hi> is a mighty Hunter, ever purſuing our fearful Hearts, that he may chaſe them from their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and ſhelter, and then ſurprize, take, and ſlay them. His Toils are the Pleaſures of the World, his Darts are a Thouſand Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, his Hounds are profane and wicked men, and what pains doth this Enemy of mankind refuſe? ſo that he may but compaſs his ends, by entangling us in wretched bondage, and enſlaving us under the dominion of Sin?</p>
               <p>He hath ſometimes endeavoured to enthral me by a handſome Face, whiſpering it out as a Ray of thy faireſt Light: and hath made uſe of the Gloworm Luſtre in two ſparkling Eyes to lead me out of thy way, into a Night of error, and when therein, now would he ſcare me with the ſeverity of thy Juſtice, anon lull me aſleep with the exceſs of thy Mercy; and then divert me by the evil cuſtoms of others, or charm me by my own bad Inclinations, perſwading by falſe and carnal Reaſonings.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:64837:20"/>
               <p>But, deareſt God how little doth the allurements of this <hi>Circaean</hi> World bewitch us? how heavily do the Goads of Senſe drive us on? how ſoon are the jugglings of the grand Impoſtor manifeſt when our Souls are directed, defended, and inſtructed by thy Goodneſs? Let the greedy purſuers pitch their Nets and make ready their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows upon the String, all their deſignes and Bows ſhall be broken by thy commiſerating care, O Lord.</p>
               <p>If at any time the many incentives to Sin do take hold of me I truſt by thy helping hand to recover my Liberty.</p>
               <p>'Tis true my bleſſed Redeemer! theſe Eyes of mine have ſtrangely confined their happineſs within the proportions of external Beauties. Tis true my Mouth hath not ecchoed thy Glories, but proved the Temple of Senſualities, my Heart hath rebelled againſt thee, and ſworn allegiance to the World, my Hands would not hold that puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thou requireſt in them, nor would my Fancy be leſs than my God. For my own Opinion hath Exacted my Worſhip, and I have not been moved at all towards Offices of Charity; &amp; in Acts of Faith have been weak and wavering.</p>
               <p>But yet Lord 'tis as true that the Devil all this while hath gone cunningly about me, to watch and to hedg in my ways that I might not eſcape his artifices; ſo that my failings have been occaſioned leſs by my own naughtiness than by his, and chiefly through his cunning Traps and devices, whereby my unwary Fooliſhneſs hath been inveigled.</p>
               <p>Now that I can find my ſelf in ſome ſuch freedom as Repentance brings along with it. I can diſcern the Devil's malice, and Sin's Fetters broken, my Senſe being led in Triumph by my Reaſon. I rally all my Spiritual Forces for the ſervice of my God, and for the Worſhip of that goodneſs which hath rendered me ſuch a mighty Object of it.</p>
               <p>Mine Eyes ſhall ſummon all their Viſive Powers to look up unto <hi>Jeſus,</hi> my Mouth ſhall be no longer as ſounding Braſs or as a crakt Trumpet, giving falſe allarms, but like a Seraphim's touched with the fire of thine Altar to eccho forth Thanks and holineſs to the Lord.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.25, 26.</note> My Heart ſhall throw all its affections (now Circumciſed) at the Feet of thy Grace, and my Hands ſhall be lift up continually to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore and to praiſe thy Mercies, O my God; becauſe thou only by the Rays of thy Favour canſt enlighten my Soul in ſuch a manner as that it may drop no more into the Darkneſs of Sin.</p>
               <p>All our humane Strengths are nothing worth; no more to be truſted too than the Reeds of <hi>Egypt;</hi> all our ſafety and refuge lies in thy Power. The welfare of my little World depends on his Arm who hath made all the other Worlds,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 26.6, 7.</note> and hanged the Univerſe upon Nothing, ſtretching forth the Globe over the empty place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6 (125)" type="step__Psalm">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:64837:20"/>
               <head>The ſixth Step on the ſixth PSALM of Degrees, being the 125 PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Qui confidunt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>O Ye Sons of mortal men,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.5.</note> how long will ye turn your Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies into weapons of Sin, your Souls into Veſſels of Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, your Glory into Shame; your Shame into your Boaſt? in believing Vanities, and ſeeking after falſe things? On what Rock but Chriſt can you anchor the Hopes of your Salvation and Eternity?</p>
               <p>Will ye truſt the fading Beauties of Fleſh and Blood, which are ſuperfluous gifts of Nature, vaniſhed in a moment, ſcarcely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained or taken notice of before they take their leave and are gone?</p>
               <p>Will ye confide on the Vigor and ſtrength of youth? Know Death makes no diſtinction of ages, and after a ſhort ſpace of time both Youth and Health are diſſolved into the imperfections of decrepid years.</p>
               <p>But perhaps ye will truſt (as ye doat) upon the worldly Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours? but ponder a while what Weights they are; and like Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaïcal burthens too grievous for moſt good men to carry. Experience ſhews that too many, even of the beſt, by the deſire or Act of Ruling others grow irregular themſelves, and diſordering their own thoughts and quiet thereby, diſtemper their felicities, if not debauch their Souls: and who ſo truſts in uncertain Riches is worſe than a Goſpel Fool. <q>Gold is but a Waſp though it look yellow, it hath Wings to fly away from us, and ſtings to leave behind it at its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, even ſuch ſtings as are like Goads, apt to puſh on our greedy and brutiſh appetites to the moſt ſordid and ſinful Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But ye would have a Cordial made up of all theſe ingredients, that rare Catholicon called Worldly felicity, which ye think might recover and ſecure the Spirits from all thoſe Qualmes and Lypothy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that many times ſeize upon them, notwithſtanding all your falſe jollities and merry Companions. But alas what is any happineſs of this lower Globe, but like it ſelf turning about. <q>'Tis but a Scene upon this Theatre, 'tis ſhifted and changed often from one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and appears always moving and inconſtant, as long as this lifes <hi>Opera</hi> is acting.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Truſt then in God, and in God alone, for if you be under his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection you need fear neither the Infirmities of Life nor the Injuries of Death.</p>
               <p>Let God be your Honour, Joy, Delight, and Treaſure; in him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts all Happineſs and Glory. Wherefore,</p>
               <p>Bleſſed God, as long as I am ſheltered by thy Divine Goodneſs, I will not fear the Tongues of this evil World, nor the Venom of that moſt evil One, let them joyn all the force of their Malice and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſneſs
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64837:21"/>together, I will remain firm and unſhaken like Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> and baffle their attempts and deride their ineffectual fury.</p>
               <p>The good Angels are appointed by thy great care over us, to be a watchful Guard and Bulwark for our weakneſs, and they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Mountains of ſtrength</hi> from the excellency of their natures and thy ſupporting Grace. But for all that they are not ſtrong enough (or rather not commiſſioned) to keep us always from the attacks of Sin, or from the Snares of the Devil.</p>
               <p>Doubtleſs thoſe Guardian Spirits direct us to Good, and very oft do turn us from Evil.</p>
               <p>But alas the pravity of our Nature makes it not ſtill capable of Angel-like perſwaſion, we are ſo immerſed in the ſatisfaction of our Luſts, and ſo inured to ſinful compliancies, that we have neither Ear nor Heart left us to liſten to the Whiſpers of Holy Spirits. We ſtill want O Lord! thy Admonitions, Aſſiſtance, and Conduct; 'tis to the Glory of thy Omnipotence onely, that I owe my ſafety. Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth I live with a chearful truſt ſprung from the greatneſs of thy Mercy, that thou wilt ever ſtand by my Soul in its frequent perils, and every action of my Life ſhall be ſmiled on with the favour of thy preſence, and with the direction of thy Will.</p>
               <p>For, as the Mountains give a defence and ſhelter round about the City of God, ſo God (who is the Rock of Ages, a vaſt Mountain of Power and Charity) will continually ſuccor and ſecure his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p>Since 'tis the peculiar effect of thy gracious Providence, O my God! to favour and defend ſuch who (relying on thy Pity) ſtill implore thy help, and Sanctuary themſelves under thy Providence; this is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready to lend a helping hand to ſuch as rightly ask it, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſometimes the Righteous Cauſe is oppreſſed by wicked Judges, and Cruelty domineers over Goodneſs, and the Purple of Tyrants is double dyed in the Blood of Innocents, yet all this is done upon righteous and wiſe grounds.</p>
               <p>Thereby thou haſt a mind, O Lord! to try the Conſtancy of thy Servants, to Correct their Errors, to exerciſe their Patience, to brighten or refine their Graces, or elſe thou wouldſt have them ſerve for excellent patterns and directions for others, that they may become thy Portion, and be fit to addreſs themſelves to thee, and then thou ſuffereſt not their Slavery to be tedious, nor their Rod too heavy. Becauſe they who are thus Obedient both to thy preceptive and providential Will are thy Children,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.5, 6, 7.</note> whom thou Chaſtiſeſt as a Father, and wilt not ſuffer the Scourge of the Wicked to dwell long upon thine Inheritance,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.4.</note> eſpecially when it earneſtly begs Relief.</p>
               <p>It would be no leſs contrary to that Dear Relation thou ſtandeſt in to us, than to the proper goodneſs of thy Nature, not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the fury of the impious, didſt not thou hook up Leviathan in dne time, it might be dangerous, that thy weak and infirm Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples (waving thy protection) would depart from thee, and either abandon themſelves to Vice (charmed by the ſhort proſperity of evil doers) or elſe grow fearful of Perſecution, and ſo put forth their hands to Iniquity, and render themſelves uncapable of thy Compaſſion.</p>
               <p>Therefore moſt Gracious Lord do not forſake them who adore the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64837:21"/>greatneſs of thy Love and Wiſdom, and ſtudy to obſerve the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs of thy Will and Pleaſure. Heap thy bounties on their Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which hath no other end but God and Righteouſneſs. O how bleſſed is the Man who by the integrity of his Affection, hath fouled neither Hand nor Tongue in the blemiſh or blood of his Neighbour! How bleſſed is he that by not obeying the uſurpations of Sin, hath not made his Reaſon cloſe Priſoner to his Concupiſcence! He is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo bleſt, who content with what he hath, would not robb nor envy the enjoyments of others. And he is bleſt too, that by the ſincerity of his Behaviour, by the probity of his Life, by the faithfulneſs of his Heart, by the innocence of his Eyes, hath endeavoured to fit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for the High-calling whereunto he is called in Jeſus Chriſt; and thereby gain thy favour, and work out his own Salvation.</p>
               <p>I am aſſured O Lord that thou powereſt forth the Treaſure of thy Bleſſings on them who make ſtreight paths for their Feet, who keep the way of Righteouſneſs, and are as conſtant as Couragious to reſiſt all Vice; ſince to accommodate the Thoughts, and fix the Will to thy Diſpenſations, is the way to get Chriſt, and to be found in him, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our own Righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>But on the contrary, Thoſe who forget thy greatneſs, O Lord! and fall down to the Worſhip of themſelves; thoſe who enter the wrong way into their Mother's Womb, and embowel the Earth to ſteal away her Treaſure, and ſeem to have no other end thereby than to bury their Souls and Hopes therein; Thoſe who being ſwallowed up in Voluptuouſneſs believe no other Paradice than the delights of Fleſh and Bloud: or thoſe who place next their own misfortunes, every proſperous event of others, ſuch as choak all Virtue by imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous appetites; and Sacrifice their beſt faculties unto Fury and Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; turning all Sobriety and Reaſon out of doors. Laſtly, ſuch as being loſt to themſelves, and in their own Opinions too, ſometimes knowing not how to wake themſelves out of the Lethargy of Vice, nor get up beyond the terms of nothing (that is, Sin and Vanity.) Such as all theſe are, I ſay, theſe unhappily curſed ones, ſhall be ſtruck down from Heaven's glorious preſence, like <hi>Nimrod</hi>'s Gyants, with hot Thunderbolts, they ſhall be confounded with <hi>Babel</hi>'s Workmen, and become the wretched Objects of the ſeverity of ſuch Corrections as are given by a Hand no leſs Powerfull and Juſt, than Jealous and Pure. They ſhall feel the Scorching of thoſe immortal Flames, which yet can never burn out their Spots, ſince they have ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered themſelves Heirs of Wrath, and Children of the Devil; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Righteous (before-mentioned, ſuch as may be ſet far from theſe Goats) bleſt with thy Love and Protection, O Lord, ſhall enjoy the ſerenity of that peace which reſides in thy favour, and ſurpaſſeth our Underſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7 (126)" type="step__Psalm">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:64837:22"/>
               <head>The ſeventh Step on the ſeventh PSALM of Degrees, being the 126 PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>In Convertendo Dominus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>O My God! how can I expreſs the Conſolation of my Soul? My Words are loſt in my joy of Heart, and can break forth but lamely at my Lips, for I behold my ſelf Redeemed, I find my ſelf delivered alſo from the dangerous Labyrinth of my winding Errours, thanks be to thy goodneſs only.</p>
               <p>The confuſed Chaos of my Life hath been called to by thy Word, and looked on by the Beams of thy Grace, nay, diſtinguiſhed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by thy Son into a new Lump, a new Converſion.</p>
               <p>The miſchiefs of my guiltineſs are not aggravated by the continual Remorſe of Conſcience, but my ſteps are directed by ſweet methods how to keep thy Statutes to the end.</p>
               <p>Terrene Objects have now no priviledge to control my Thoughts. My Delights and Deſires retain no other reliſh than of a Crucified Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. Mine Ears took up with the name of Jeſus, cannot underſtand or liſten to the low dumb Muſick of Vanity. Mine Eyes are fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcinated by one glance of thine, and follow none of thoſe Wildfires which did uſe to miſguide them. My Taſt ſavouring the things of God, the Glories of another State, diſguſts thoſe Treats which Satan entertained me withal (while he would have me take Stones for Bread:) All thoſe Appetites which mere moſt my own, and ſeemed Connatural to a deluded mind, (having left me nothing but Shame and Sorrow) they take their leave of me (I truſt for ever) not to return any more (with ſeven Devils worſe than themſelves) to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs me.</p>
               <p>Wherefore advanced by ſo much Grace, and replete with ſo much Happineſs as to find Favour in thy ſight, O moſt gracious Lord! how great is my Jubile! how infinite my Conſolation!</p>
               <p>Methinks the rough and narrow way to Heaven is now made plain and ſmooth before my Face, and my Feet are not apt to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo as they did formerly, but are more ſteadily guided to the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of thy Commands: and I find theſe, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, exceeding broad on every ſide of me, that I have no Temptation (without much perverſeneſs) to depart from them. My Conſcience doth not Goad me with unſound Repentance, or unſafe Deſpair. Mine Eyes do not ſtay themſelves on terrene Objects, except it be to make them more contemptible, even to my outward ſenſe. The Sin that erewhile was the Idol of my enjoyments, is now the Subject of my Hate and Abhorrence. My Actions are levelled at the love of Virtue. My Deſires are converted (from the enhanſing my Account, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning on further on the ſcore of guilt) to the making all the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction I can, for the Debts I have contracted, and my hope is grounded on thy Mercy (not on my poor endeavours) for the raiſing up the Pillar of my conſtant happineſs.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:64837:22"/>
               <p>And can the Mouth that is filled with ſuch good things ſavour any thing elſe than the repetition of thy Bounty, and the exceſſes of thy Love? Surely my Tongue ſhall be now as the Pen of a ready Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and being urged on by the Solace of my Heart, (ſhall like the Angels by whom thou doſt ſuccour me) reſound the Praiſes, and the Proofs of thy Divinity, far and near, by thy ſaving and conſerving of my ſtate.</p>
               <p>O deareſt Lord! thou haſt condeſcended, more than once, to ſeek and to ſave that which was in danger to be loſt, and to call not the Righteous but Sinners to thee! How doth the particular care thou takeſt of Sinners, even to this day, encreaſe and burniſh the Glories of thy Name, <hi>Jeſus!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the very Heathens view the Smoak of Senſualities to a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appearance, and the brighter Sparks of holy Affections mounting up in lieu of the other in us. When they obſerve the Rebellions of our Hearts turned into Evidences of Obedience, and ſhall behold ſuch a Worm as I am, the greateſt of Sinners, no longer a ſervant of Sin but a contemner of the World and a reſiſter of the Devil; ſurely they will glorify the Operations of thy Power, and the mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thy love, in the Pardon and Converſion of ſo frail a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>Even thoſe very Animals (as the Apoſtle calls them) who were loſt in the Labyrinths of their vicious Habits,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14, 15.</note> and ſought not the Clew of Repentance to help them out of Perdition.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note> They ſhall be converted unto thee, through the demonſtratio of thy goodneſs to others they ſhall be convinced (as the <hi>Idiotae</hi> were in the Primitive Church) and be conſtrained to magnify thy Kindneſs, implore thy Mercies, and advance thy Praiſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>For to ſee a man who in himſelf is poor and naked, and ſtript by his Infernal Enemies of all ſuccour, diveſted of all good, and left in a more wretched condition than the wounded Travellor to <hi>Jericho,</hi> or than the <hi>Daemoniack</hi> among the Tombs to behold ſuch an one cloathed and in his right mind, dreſſed in the needful habit of Reaſon, and trimmed up with the ornaments of Grace, inſtalled in the Throne of Piety, which is at the Feet of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and there inſtructed better than under a <hi>Gamaliel.</hi>
                  </q> What an Argument of Wonder may be ſuch an example? and ſuch an one I wiſh to be; that while I ſtir up admiration by the recount of what thou haſt done for my Soul I may perſwade the un-reſolved that thou canſt do far more for them, and that theſe are but ſmall inſtances of thy Almightineſs in reſpect of its infinity. <q>Thou canſt doe, thou canſt ſuffer, much more for the good of Mankind, if ſo be they will but credit thy mighty Works, and not be like <hi>Bethſaida</hi> and <hi>Capernaum.</hi>
                  </q> Woe be to ſuch as believe not the marvellous teſtimonies of thy good will to the Sons of Men. For didſt not thou, Eternal Lord! incorporate thy ſelf with our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as if thou didſt eſteem it braver than thy own Divinity? Art thou not ready to waſh out the ſtains of our Nature even with the Life and Blood of thy aſſumed one which hath ſo wonderfully over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valued ours? Wouldſt thou not load thy moſt glorious perſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move our Burthens? taking off the preſſures of our baſe Captivity by the perfect eaſe of thy Yoke?</p>
               <p>Lord Jeſu! thou haſt humbled thy ſelf to a ſervile ſtate, to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64837:23"/>upon earth, to reconcile contradictions, the Son of God, and the Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> and ſo to unite the moſt ſinful to the moſt Holy, though not as they are impure, as themſelves; but as cleanſed by thy Grace, and Redeemed to be thine. By theſe effectual merits of thy working upon Earth by Water and Blood, by thy Tears and Prayers, by thine A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gony and Bloody Sweat, by thy Croſs and Paſſion, and by the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Holy Ghoſt (though he be grieved alſo) in the handing of the benefits thou haſt purchaſed for ſuch Enemies as we have been, both to them, to thy Spirit, to thy Love, and to thee. The ſenſe of theſe over-flowing Bounties like ſtrong perfumes to a weak body, might eaſily diſſipate my Spirits and untie my being, I might be ſoon unlooſed from Life and all the World, as I deſire to be, by the full apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of their Vigor. In the mean time good God accept my Heart, all Jubile, and Thankſgiving, for that thou haſt dealt ſo ſtrangely with thy Servant as to give me enough, nay all, yea, more than this All, far more then my Capacities or the Univerſe may contain. I have all and abound, and what more can a Sinner expect or Receive? What more can a God do for ſuch a Sinner? Yes, he can ſtill enlarge my meaſures for Reception, as well as fill them more and more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Eternity. Bleſs the Lord then always, O my Soul! and leaſt at any time thy Joys ſhould flag or leſſen; be daily taking preſervatives againſt Sin, and get farther from the Plague of this mortal conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from the Offending of ſo Good a Lord; O could I fly out of the reach of ſuch infection, I might then judge my ſatisfaction no leſs ſecured than unſpeakable! whereas the frequent receipts of thy Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs paid here with cold affections or ungrateful acts, caſt too oft a a damp over the Wings of my joy, and is a ſad abatement of that Towring comfort which I might pitch upon in the Expreſſions of thy Love and mine.</p>
               <p>Free me therefore I beſeech thee, deareſt Lord! from the Bondage of my Corruptions, Suffer not the wounds of Original Sin to rankle or gangrene in my Heart, leaſt theſe become ſo outragious as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe or fear the help of thy Hand for its healing and binding up.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Such a Wolf did once eat off the Breaſts of the beloved Spouſe, the Church of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and turned her to a dry and barren Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But, Lord, prevent the ſpoil that ſuch ravenous furies would make in thy Vineyard, and heal our Souls though we have Sinned againſt thee.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Let not the filthyneſs of my actual Offences poiſon the health or Salvation of my State: let not worldly greatneſs or ſenſual pleaſures enveigle my Thoughts from thy worſhip, to other ſervices (which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are meer ſlaveries and the baſeſt of ſuch.) But as the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winds (or <hi>Sirocco</hi>'s) do uſually impregnate and ſwell up Torrents, ſo let the Gifts and Graces of thy Holy Spirit augment all probity and Virtue in my Soul, tending to the Ocean of Eternal Perfections. And farther impower my Heart to be truly penitent that the Springs from thence running through my Eyes, may help to waſh off the ſpots which have beſmeared my Conſcience.</p>
               <p>I Know, Great God! that whoſoever doth exerciſe himſelf in the Olympicks of true Devotion, he that outbraves the faſhions or flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries of the World, he that adores thy Greatneſs with humility and fixes his hopes on Geleſtial Objects: He it is that ſowes to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64837:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuch a Seed that will inſtantly bear Thirty fold in the return of more Grace, and hereafter an hundred in the Harveſt of Glory. And he that ſheds the Teats of Religious mourning upon Earth ſhall reap Comfort and Joy in Immortality, when all Tears ſhall be wiped off, and Sorrows and Sighings ſhall melt away.</p>
               <p>Give me then leave to attend thee with all ſorts of the Grain of Tears. I would weep for the pardon of my Guilt, to ſave my ſelf from the Foulneſs of it, I would weep for diſpleaſing thee, as for the deſerving thy Vengeance, and this to quench the fervours of my Luſts. I would weep over the Miſeries of our preſent Mortality, to ſolace my down-caſt Spirit in her clayie Priſon and Relegation. I would weep for my <q>
                     <hi>Tamuz,</hi> for my <hi>Adonis,</hi> for my <hi>Adonai,</hi> for my ſelf and for others,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezech.</hi> 8.14.</note> for my vile Idolatries and Proſtitutions, for my Spiritual Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, for my own and others manifold defilements, according as thou, dear Lord! didſt adviſe thy people when thou didſt command them ſaying, <hi>Weep not for me, but weep for your ſelves;</hi> and I will weep for thee alſo, O my <hi>Adonai,</hi> my Love, my Dove, my Undefiled one, for having treated thee ſo ſavagely and occaſioned others to affront thee too, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to procure eaſe and ſatisfaction to thy ſelf, to others, and to me.</q> Even to the ſcrewing up of the Joys and Harmony of the Celeſtial Manſions. And Laſtly, I will weep to encreaſe my Thirſt of that Country which thou haſt promiſed us above, that I may fill up ſuch a <hi>Nilus</hi> here, as may render the <hi>Egypt</hi> of my Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more fruitful under all thy Providences.</p>
               <p>Now that I find my ſelf embarraſſed in great ſtreights, in a World Malevolent to real Bliſs, where the Prince of it is ſtill trying the ſtrength of my Conſtancy, and Senſe is offering violence to my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, where Company by ill examples and incitements increaſe my frailties, where Beauty, Ambition, Honours and Anger, Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Sloth, would play the <hi>Dalilahs</hi> to abuſe and ſnare me; give me leave, O God! while I am a Travelor in the Vale of Miſery to dig up Fountains of Penitential Waters, to cleanſe off the Scales from my Eyes which have been ſo often blinded by the treacheries of my and Enemies, and thine.</p>
               <p>O that I could now cultivate the ground of my Heart by Faſting, Prayers and Tears, by deeds of Charity and Offices of Devotion and then with the <hi>Four and twenty Elders</hi> in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> demiſe at thy Feet ſuch Crowns and Palmes, ſuch Talents and Abilities as thou haſt put into my Hands to account for in thy Kingdom; for thine is the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, Power and Glory, and thou art onely worthy to receive the Profits of thine own. No Soul can taſt more joy than his that can approach unto thy dreadful Throne with a Conſcience ſo void of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence (as not to accuſe it ſelf) and with a ſmall treaſure of good Works (ſuch a Preſent as the Patriark ſent the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Governour, <hi>Gen.</hi> 43.11.) which may bring whole ſheaves again to us.</p>
               <p>Finally, Grant that all my Faculties may count themſelves bound to honour thy name for ever; that my Heart may be all on fire for thy Love, and my Affections own no other Object nor employ but thy Service, nor my Senſes reliſh other Beauties, Hopes, or Acqueſts than thoſe of Heaven and Eternity.</p>
               <p>Let me have with thee all the Conditions and Qualifications of a true Votary in Serving, Imitating and Suffering, ſerving thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64837:24"/>with all my Powers, Copying thy Actions with all diligence, and enduring all oppoſitions with an humble fortitude, that I may reap the fruit of Holineſs, and its end Everlaſting Life. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8 (127)" type="step__Psalm">
               <head>The eighth Step on the eighth PSALM of Degrees, being the 127 PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Niſi Dominus aedificaverit.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>MY Soul is ſo beleaguered with dangers, that like a long beſieged City; 'twill fall at laſt into the Enemies Hands, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be relieved by thine extream Compaſſion, what pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful ſuccour hath all things beſides thee brought? alas I can hardly owne that I have been helped even by the beſt preaching of thy Miniſters, nay, what good doth <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets to my wretched State? All thy moſt holy Doctrine, O thou Holy of Holies! all thoſe moſt excellent patterns and precepts of Saints and Martyrs afforded to me, reach not far enough to jogg my Senſes out of the Lethargy of Sin, unleſs thou ſtretch forth thy Arm, O God! (even Chriſt out of thy own Boſom) and put him into mine, that that Sun of Righteouſneſs may enlighten and enliven my dark Breaſt. This hath devoted all its affections to thy ſervice, 'tis true, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it cannot keep them to their duty without thy conſtant over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looking of them. Although in thy holy Sacraments thou breatheſt down thy Spirit for us to receive, what care do we take (for all thine) to Welcom, Houſe, or entertain it by the ſmall remainders of Faith, Hope, or Charity.</p>
               <p>And as all their Efforts are vain and fruitleſs, who toile to build up their worldly ſatisfactions without thy bleſſings; ſo is all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry of the Mind to no purpoſe for the acquiring or preſerving of Grace, without thy good will or Divine aſſiſtance, ſince from thee we have our principles and beginnings, our conſervation, protection, and perfection.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Without thee (as thou haſt told us) we can do nothing but we muſt likewiſe know that thou art not far from any one of us, nor forſakeſt ſuch as ſeek thee truly.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Many do miſ-conjecture that the height of Walls, the depth of Waters, the thickneſs of Works, the courage of Men, the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Arms, the fulneſs of Proviſions, the watchfulneſs of Guards, and the wiſdom of Commanders will ſecure any Regular Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; when alas all the Ramparts will founder, all the Baſtions and Lines fall in together, (like the walls of <hi>Jericho</hi>) the Curtains will drop down, or rend in pieces, (being too thin and ſleight to keep out an Enemy) while wrapped in them the ſleepy Centinels ſhall be carried off to Eternal Slumbers, unleſs thy Providence and Protection,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64837:24"/>O Lord of Hoſts be over ſuch a Fortreſs, for it is thy favour that muſt be its ſtrong Tower and Rock of defence, and Magazine of ſafety; without that all we can do ſignifies nothing. How far can humane induſtry advance to raiſe a man up (like <hi>Jeremiah</hi> out of the Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon) from the pit of Sin, or deſpair? or to ſupport him in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence? till thou ſayeſt the Comfortable Edict, <hi>I will be thou clean?</hi> 'Tis true the Angels are miniſtring Spirits, and Holy men help inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally to the conſervation of Grace, and to the diſpoſing of our Minds to good by their exhortations and examples. And,</p>
               <p>'Tis certain that I am not ſeldom affected with the conſciouſneſs of my provocations, ſo that I reſolve then vigorouſly to ſpend the reſidue of my dayes amongſt the Rigors of an Auſtere Repentance: while my Remembrance ſhames me with the Thoughts of thy abuſed patience (which muſt needs be turned into fury, and this be imbittered by delay.) Yet for all this without thy ſpecial Grace and particular aſſiſtance all my Reſolutions are but Spiders Webbs, my ſtrongeſt attempts but as Stubble before a conſuming fire, very weak and ridiculous motions. It is not in Man (ſaith the Prophet) to direct his Steps.</p>
               <p>Therefore truſt not, O mortal men! either to your ſelves or to your poſſeſſions; truſt not your enjoyments of great Knowledge, or of great Strength, no not of the chief Natural or Corporeal Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, no more than you would credit the turning Wheel of <hi>Fortune,</hi> or the Top of worldly Pomp and Honours.</p>
               <p>Can ye think by robbing your Eyes of Sleep, your Minds of Reſt, your Limbs of Eaſe, or your Bodies of Health, ye may do any thing on your own ſcore, to gain the applauſe of Heaven, or to throw open the Gates of Paradiſe? No, no, the Roots of your Merit ſhould be ſet on another Ground, it is not a Plant that will grow in the barren ſoil of our Earth, we muſt have God's daily Cultivation, his Love, his Shelter, and his Sun too, or elſe we ſhall go without it.</p>
               <p>And to obtain ſome worthineſs of thy Regard, ſome favour in thy ſight, a ſound and ſincere reliance upon Chriſt doth avail more than all the Watchings, Faſtings, Auſterities and Rods, which ſome make ſuch a buſtle withall, and too often to little purpoſe; for their riſing at Midnight or before Day, is but a walking in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; their arrogant reliance on their own Performances, is but increaſing the difficulties of ſuch achievements as depend not on our own Strength or Merit; but on God's Free-will, and his alone good pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Aſſiſt me therefore, O moſt gracious Lord! with ſuch a Grace as may gratifie my humble requeſts, and graciouſly receive the ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my Heart in all its acts of Penance with ſincerity of Addreſs, of Truſt, and Obedience to thee, and to thee onely, (for to which of the Saints may I turn?)</p>
               <p>That although I have been long embraced within the Arms of Sin, I may now break away from that Harlot, and from the bondage of my Guilt, and fly unto thee for a place of reſt in the Boſom of thy Favour and Compaſſion.</p>
               <p>Lord ſuffer not the naughtineſs of my Heart to inveigle me to any further expectation of Comfort, or hope of Satisfaction, than in thoſe things that are above, and there promis'd me by thy Truth and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64837:25"/>Let not Worldly concerns, or poor tranſitory Prizes allure my Soul, which ſtoops too oft at low Objects; ſhe ſhould tower more out of ſight of Earth, like a Bird of Paradiſe, and direct her mount to that Summit, or height where ſhould be her Airie, and which was her Country, Ah! did ſhe ply her Wings thitherward (like thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt Dove) ſhe would not be endangered by the Floods of Humane unhappineſs, ſhe would reach home with her <hi>Olive</hi> and <hi>Myrtle</hi> bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, with Peace, and Purity.</p>
               <p>While Imploying all the Labours of my Life and longings of my Heart after a ſight of God in ſuch Righteouſneſs, (as Peace and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs bring along with them) I my ſelf might be ſecured both in Life and in Death; and I ſhould find Death but as a ſleep and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as an Inheritance, long promiſed to the Faithful, and laid up for us in thoſe promiſes; as laid out in that other Life, where thoſe who are faithful unto Death may expect a full ſatisfaction of their Pains, Hopes and deſires, and meet with a farther Solace in a Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of one another, and of all their Fellow-brethren, even the whole flock of Chriſt; which ſhall then appear in his Preſence, and enter into his Joy, and triumph in his Courts to all the Ages of an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Eternity.</p>
               <p>I will therefore, O my God! aſſert my ſelf thy Creature, the work of thy Almighty Power, the Fruit of the Body of Chriſt, begotten again to a lively hope by his blood, and ſeeking Regeneration by his Ordinances, and by my Faith; ſo that I may not love the World nor the things of it, but do the will of our Father which is in Heaven.</p>
               <p>But doth it not require much Sweat, vaſt Pains and violent Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, and very great Self-denial, to enter in at the ſtrait Gate, and to walk worthy of the Denomination of a Son of God? Yea ſurely. 'Tis therefore needful to leave off the purſuit of all thoſe vain com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placencies which have ſerved onely to amuſe and to deceive me here below.</p>
               <p>'Tis needfull, O my Soul! that thou being armed by devout Prayer and Faſting, ſhouldeſt be ſober and watchful to repell the moſt fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious attacks of his Temptations, who is come forth againſt thee like a ravenous Lion. 'Tis needful for thee to make Reaſon thy Pilot, Religion thy Load-ſtar for thy better paſſage through the waves of this troubleſome Life, and if thou ſteereſt wiſely in the faithleſs Sea of this World, weathering all the ſtormes of Impetuous affections, thou mayeſt at laſt arrive at the Haven where thou wouldeſt be: and as the feigned Son of <hi>Jupiter</hi> is ſaid to overcome the many-headed Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, ſo thou mayeſt by thy ſeveral Labours in Charity, Love, Faith, Repentance, and Reſtitution, ſubdue the <hi>Hydra</hi> of Sin, and approve thy ſelf a Child of God according to the Apoſtles aſſertion.</p>
               <p>Now thou mayeſt underſtand that the Sons of God are like Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows in the Hands of a Gyant, they wound the Hearts of Gods Enemies, and ſcatter ſuch as delight in Miſchief; deſtroying and beating down what is evil, quickening Faith and working Love in the Godly; and the Effects of ſuch Divine Inſtruments as theſe, are the diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of Sin, the feeding the Hungry, Cloathing the Naked, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couring the Poor, entertaining the Stranger, viſiting the Priſoner, freeing the Captive, burying the Slain, correcting the Obſtinate, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelling the Ignorant, comforting the Afflicted, aſſiſting the Weak,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64837:25"/>forgiving the Injurious, and praying for the Perſecutors. In fine, all the moſt accompliſhed performances of the Memory, Will and Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, are but as ſo many barbed Arrows put into our Hands by God to be ſhot againſt his Enemy Satan, and (the maker of the Devil,) Sin.</p>
               <p>How happy then is the Chriſtian Warrior, who makes uſe of theſe Weapons! How happy is the <hi>Jonathan</hi> that can ſtrip himſelf of his Harneſs of Worldly mindedneſs, of the full Quiver of his Luſts, of the Girdle of Self-love (wherewith he is too often girded) for the ſake of the Son of <hi>David!</hi> He is Lovely as much as Lowly, who can hate himſelf and all things here below. He is Juſt and ſtrong indeed, who can do Violence to his own Intereſt for the greater benefit thereby to his Neighbour. He is wiſe, that can chuſe a Saviour's Thorns rather than the ſweeteſt Flowers of Sin, which are but for a ſeaſon. He is Noble, that makes uſe of Greatneſs chiefly for the Glory of God. He is Rich, that will laviſh his <hi>Mammon</hi> here to make himſelf Friends therewith hereafter. And he in truth, is the alone happy man who with ardent affection and continued watchfulneſs hears, receives and obeys the truth of thy Work, and allows no Reſting place, no Ark, nor any <hi>Aſylum,</hi> to unlawful deſires or inordinate affections with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him.</p>
               <p>Such men as theſe before-mentioned, they are who in the midſt of the Fire, the Thunder and Lightnings, Cries and Terrors of the laſt Judgment, ſhall never be daunted in the preſence of their Judge, nor by the Indictment of their Accuſers.</p>
               <p>For being kept in perfect Peace by the ſtay of their Souls on thee, good Lord! they are ſafely brought into the Harbour of a quiet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and under the ſhelter of a mighty <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who is able to ſave them to the uttermoſt from all their Adverſaries, and from all ſuch accuſations as may not then touch the juſtified by Chriſt, although they may ſerve to convince other Sinners, and diſplay the Ungodlineſs of Sin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9 (128)" type="step__Psalm">
               <head>The ninth Step on the ninth PSALM of Degrees, being the 128 PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Beati, qui timent.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>HE that would gain the Beatitude of thy Favour, O Lord! muſt of neceſſity fear thy greatneſs and obey thy precepts, ſo that he is the bleſſed man upon Earth that knows ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly how to guide his Feet into the ways of Peace, into the paths of thy Commandments, and doth meet with no other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences in his way, than the doubts he may ſometimes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter about thy Love and Favour to him. The fear of thy Power,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64837:26"/>and the Reverence of thy greatneſs, is ſo needful, even for the very beſt,<note place="margin">Dan. 4.31, 32. Ier. 51.9.</note> elſe why hath thy juſteſt Vengeance armed it ſelf with Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſtrike down the preſumptuous? Why haſt thou by Fire from Heaven extinguiſhed the memorial of Tranſgreſſors?</p>
               <p>Why didſt thou command the Waters to climb above the higheſt Mountains, but that thou mighteſt overcome the greateſt Sinners? and ſhew how by thy wrath (as by thy Love) thou couldeſt hide a multitude of faults. Thou haſt bred Monſters within men by conſcious apprehenſions, and often ſurroundeſt thoſe <hi>Scilla's</hi> with terrors of guilt. Thou haſt many times ſuffered thine Enemies to puniſh one another by their Cruelties. And not ſeldom by Earthquakes, by panick Confuſions or Fears, by Portentous Signes, and ſtrange<note n="*" place="margin">Such as were <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently heard before the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi>
                  </note> Voices, thou wouldſt inſtruct all them who liſten to thee, ſpeaking either on Earth or from Heaven, and thou wouldeſt alſo correct the infidelity of others, and thereby convince ſuch how thou art to be feared.</p>
               <p>Yet ſurely the fear that is ſtruck into us by the Effects of thy Power is not ſo kindly welcom to thee, nor ſo agreeable to us, as that which proceeds from a ſenſe of thy Love and pity: and I know by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience that thou wouldſt be loved chiefly, becauſe thou art Long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, rather than Omnipotent; and thou haſt proved thy ſelf moſt a God by ſhewing mercy, in being not called now the Lord of Hoſts, but the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in whom dwels the fulneſs of the Godhead bodily, and in him thou art our Father which art in Heaven, Hallowed be thy Name, &amp;c. How wonderfully this advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the proof of thy Clemency above that of thy Power! to the end that mans Fear and Reverence of thee may Spring rather from his filial affection, than from thy Supreme Authority.</p>
               <p>And doubtleſs he that fears thee, O my God! out of a regard to thy Statutes, that he may not infringe them, nor hazard the Loſs of thy Favour, nor loſe the Hopes of his Adoption, or of his Admiſſion into the Joy of his Lord, he ſurely reaps the beſt of Heaven and Earth, the trueſt Comforts of this life and of a better. Therefore I wiſh all Mankind would take ſuch a Courſe as this! How health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful then would be your Sweats, how bleſſed your Pains, how profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table your Labours, O ye Mortals! who too often ſpend your Strength in vain, and your time in fruitleſs works of darkneſs. Then your Wealth would not be impaired and blaſted as 'tis now frequently by the Rapine of others,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> by the Rigour of ill ſeaſons, or by a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Croſs events, but it would be an enjoyment as ſweet as 'tis a Poſſeſſion, and ſerve for your juſt Satisfactions and Neceſſities, as well as for the profit of many more. The care you would then take to be Charitable, and the ſincerity ye would uſe in the Application of your Mammon to good purpoſes, would make it return double to you (like <hi>Job</hi>'s Eſtate) and be preſerved to you by God himſelf: who ſeing you not beſmeared with Envy or Covetouſneſs, in reſpect of theſe deceitful Goods, or miſ-led by Pride, or Worldly-mindedneſs, he would delight in your Abundance together with your ſelves, and (while ye taſted the ſweets of all your Induſtry) he, the good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-man (ſo called <hi>John</hi> c. 15. v. 4.) would alſo taſt a grateful, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a gracious Return and Reliſh of that full Cup of yours, which he had firſt put into your hand, as likewiſe of that penalty (which we may thus happily undergoe) how in the Sweat of our brows
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64837:26"/>we may eat here comfortably, and get up to God's holy Hill at laſt.</p>
               <p>For let us be convinced, 'tis by taking pains, and in the fear of the Lord, that all the Felicities of every eſtate muſt be acquired.</p>
               <p>Univerſal Nature hath no Bliſs, nor Pleaſure for ſuch as do not fear and tremble, pant, and ſtruggle after it, in Gods way. Such as do, lack nothing (ſaith the Scripture). The Stars and Elements jointly concur, not to fight againſt them (as againſt <hi>Siſera</hi>) but to pour upon them benign influences, nay the Incarnate Wiſdom of the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which is the Bridegroom of every pious, and lowly Soul, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally waters the Garden of his Spouſe, and (like the Spirit in the Blood) runs through the abſtruſeſt Chanels of the Breaſt, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times produces the Peace of God <hi>(which paſſeth all underſtanding,)</hi> ſometimes it nurtures Chaſtity (which is as admirable as rare,) now it preſents it modeſty, by which the moſt exorbitant ambitions may be checked, and then points it out to the means of acquiring true Honour. Sometimes it exhorts to the Poſſeſſion of that Heritage St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of, which is all one with a happy Eternity:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> and directs the wandring Thoughts (which were nigh loſt upon worldly Objects) to the contemplation of the Greatneſs, and of the Goodneſs of that Portion prepared in Heaven.</p>
               <p>At other times it augments the proofs of a right Charity, which gilds the way to Happineſs.</p>
               <p>And thus at laſt true Wiſdom proves a Vine, which being planted in our mortal earth, proves like <hi>Joſeph</hi> very fruitful, and brings forth Cluſters unto Holineſs, ſtretching out its Roots towards the Well of Life, and its Armes to kiſs the top of Glory, and reſts its whole force and State upon the ſufficient ſtrengths of a Saviour.</p>
               <p>Hence comes it to paſs, that all the Operations of ſuch an one as fears God, ſpring conſtantly from his Union with the Eternal Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and are very compleat acts of Probity and Vertue.</p>
               <p>His thoughts mount even to the third Heaven, not ſtooping in their flight towards mortal things, for any other reaſon, than to make it afterward force up the higher; his Heart becoms ſo emptied of Vanity, that no Impreſſions find long harbour there, but ſuch as Limn out Divine Love. His eyes enamoured with the Beauties of Heaven, meet no objects here below, but ſuch as ſeem unworthy its regards. His Tongue that perhaps had been an Eccho to the Licentiouſneſs of the Age, now utters nothing but what is full of moral concluſions for himſelf, full of good Counſels for others, and more full of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgements of God's kindneſs to all.</p>
               <p>Thoſe his deſires which were once inveigled by the prettineſs of a Face, by the poſſeſſion of Wealth, or by the vanity of Honour, now are ſettled on the Glories of Heaven, on the <hi>Indies</hi> of another World, on the Beauties of Holineſs, on the Charmes of the Grace of God, that hath appeared unto all men.</p>
               <p>And thus the men which are rightly ſaid to fear the Lord, (<hi>Mal. chap.</hi> 4.) and reverence him indeed with ſacred Worſhip, they are renewed in the Spirit of their minds, and are ſtill freſh and flouriſhing like Olive-branches in the Houſe of their God.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>They are <hi>(Feſtoons)</hi> the Garlands which crown his Temples, and imbelliſh his Triumphs for ever more. About their rich adornments
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64837:27"/>and noble ſtations, we may find enwreathed ſuch inſtructions, (as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> preſents us here) <hi>Lo! thus ſhall be done to the Man whom the King will Honour;</hi> Lo! thus ſhall he be bleſſed that feareth the Lord.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Whoſoever therefore will learn to joyn Obedience to a Devout fear, by holding down his own reſtif Will to the Law of God, and (being jealous of his natural Infirmities) prove ſtill ſollicitous to be ſafe by taking care not to offend in Thought, Word, or Deed, ſuch a man may be aſſured of Divine Grace, and the Conſequence of this both in time, and beyond it alſo.</p>
               <p>Lord, I perceive thou requireſt nothing of me but a willing mind; but that Fear, and that Obedience, that ſhould be as eaſily, as duely gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thee; and how come we to Sin, but by diſobedience? what is the chief occaſion of our offending thee, but the not dreading thine An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? If I would learn rightly how to fear, I might ſhun the Hazards both of Life and Death. Negligence for the moſt part makes us Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacious, whereas on the contrary Fear drives away neglect, deters us from Vice, learns us Diſcretion, fences the Soul againſt temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and plies it to all probity, of which in ſome ſort it may be termed the chief Cauſe. Therefore,</p>
               <p>Grant me thy Grace, O merciful God! to be qualified by the acts of Love, and Charity, to fear thy Power and Majeſty, without ceaſing (as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did,) under the greateſt temptations. Grant that being enamoured with the ſanctity of thy Precepts, I may not be perverted by the enveiglements of Sinns, nor by the vanities of this Age. Grant that looſing my Heart from all Worldly diſſoluteneſs, it may abide a Veſſel of Honour, and Purity, of Holyneſs, and Election: By theſe means, O my God! I ſhall hope thy bleſſing, and, deareſt Lord! thou canſt not deny the effects of thy Grace, towards thoſe who ſerve thee humbly, and love thee ſincerely, and truſt intirely upon thee.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, my Soul being parched up with the fervour of my Love for thee, waits like a thirſty Land, for the Dew of thy bleſſing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh it, ſo as to make it recover the verdure of its Hopes, and ſhoot up like the poor Muſtard ſeed until its Armes may reach up to Heaven, and take hold of that Glorious Eternity, which makes thy Church there Triumphant.</p>
               <p>Extend thy acouſtomed goodneſs (for thine Arm, O Lord! is not ſhortened that it cannot ſave) and anſwer, I beſeech thee, my Prayers, with ſuch Bleſſings, as are ſtill ſought for by the good, and feared by the evil, hoped for by the Faithful, and deſpaired of by the Caſt-away. For they are Sanctified Mercies, and the chief bleſſing of Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which ſecure a future Inheritance, as likewiſe many temporal Felicities, of thoſe kinds as are ordinarily thrown unto the Worſt, and but ſeldom allowed unto Gods own Children, without a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabundant meaſure of Holineſs, and devout Care; but theſe being bound up with the richeſt Jewels of the Crown, inaugurate us with the Earneſt of thy Spirit, and enſure us that after the troubleſome exile of this mortal Life, we ſhall be made Heirs of that Glorious Kingdom, which is inconceivably Happy, and Deſirable, and for which we implore thy Favour, through Chriſt Jeſus our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10 (129)" type="step__Psalm">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:64837:27"/>
               <head>The tenth Step on the tenth PSALM of Degrees, being the 129 PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Saepe expugnaverunt.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>FEar not Temptations, O my Soul! the Apoſtle ſaith, We ſhould count it all joy when we enter into them, for theſe are but to exerciſe thy Patience, to prove thy Sincerity, and to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify thy Fidelity. How canſt thou hope to arrive at Gods Favour, like one of his dear Children, unleſs thou endure the Fiery tryal?</p>
               <p>Reſiſt therefore, O my Soul! if it ſhould be even to Blood, becauſe at laſt, even by the Temptation, God can make a way for thy eſcape, and thy God ſhall be with thee, thy tribulation ſhall but compleat the worthineſs of thy condition.</p>
               <p>How oft in the more florid times of Youth, when that cooler reaſon, like a Winter fled from the Spring of Senſe, (and by the growing heat of this, the other was driven away:) then how did the great Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of my Welfare play their Game moſt cunningly, to eſtrange my Heart from due Obedience to its Maker? How oft did thoſe deadly Foes of mine make uſe of the Charmes of ſuch Beauty, as had but borrowed all its fine Feathers from Art, and adorn'd its Trophies with the ſpoils of many Graves? and all this to fetter me like a Bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave, to fix me to this lower World, ſo that I might not be able to run the way of the Commands of God, nor to find the Path of Life, and Tranquillity. Thus my Companions, whether good or bad, can witneſs againſt me, for to both indeed, (though in different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners) I have imparted the Conſpiracy of my rebellious Affections.</p>
               <p>There are ſome debauched perſons, who have too often accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied me, and there are ſome devout perſons who have admoniſhed me, when I have been in the midſt of my Extravagancies, and I muſt confeſs, (that for all the Aid I have craved, and the Advice I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, of the beſt men for the maſtering of my Senſualities,) the very Principles, and firſt motions of my Repentings have been laid at ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly, and much attacked by the Suggeſtions, and Temptations of my inviſible Foes, and by the ill examples, and falſe colours of my appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Friends, who indeed have been the mortalleſt Adverſaries to my welfare, by repreſenting Luſt to me, as an unavoidable warmth of Nature; Anger, as the Effect of my Vigorous Soul; Avarice, as the Daughter of Prudence; Idleneſs, as the Balſome of Health; Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, as the needful Magazine for the Body; Envy, as the wiſe and uſual Virtue of Emulation; Pride, as a convenient quality for High-born perſons, and to be aſſumed, together with the titles of our Anceſtors.</p>
               <p>In fine, by their Tyrannizing over my Will, they have not left tempting of me, till through their Authorities, and worſe Examples,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64837:28"/>together with my own Corruptions, I have been drawn into the fowleſt Crimes, and moſt dangerous Offences.</p>
               <p>But now being armed by the Power of thy Glorious Name, O holy <hi>Jeſus!</hi> and by the Divinity of thine Inſtructions, I hope to overcome all the Malice, and all the Violence of my Adverſaries, who ſhall be ſo loſt in their own Confuſion, and Diſappointments, as that they ſhall onely ſerve to advance the proof of my Conſtancy, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celerate the deſtruction of their own Malice.</p>
               <p>For alaſs! how often have theſe cruel hunters laid ſnares to entrap my Soul by Sin? They have allured me by the feigned ſweetneſs of Worldly Pleaſures; they have perſwaded me to offend out of a raſh confidence of Pardon; they have diverted me with ſuch Senſualities; as might ſooneſt abuſe my Conſtitution; they have entrapped me with ſuch falſe arguments, as might ſooneſt deceive the ſimple, and betray the innocent.</p>
               <p>Lord! How often have they derided thy Power, with impious, and prophane Diſcourſes, becoming the Oracles of Hell, they have vented Blaſphemies againſt thy Holieſt Name? And, Ah! too often, with Raillery, and Scorn, have they attacked my Obedience, and overthrown my obſervance of thy Precepts. Every-ways they did ſo batter my Faith, that I ſeemed to bear in my Boſom the rebukes of many, and to have the weight of their Sin upon my Shoulders; this was a Load ſo inſupportable to my weakneſs, as hereupon my Afflictions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the more grievous, by their continuance upon me in ſuch a woful manner.</p>
               <p>But Lord! that Sovereign Juſtice of thine, which deals Rewards, and Puniſhments; (and is conſtantly impartial in thy Corrections, as in thy Remunerations,) 'tis that which at laſt hath diſcovered the Cheats, defeated the force, and repulſed the pride of thoſe impious Sinners, who inſnared my Safety, contrived my Ruine, and digged Pitts (as the Prophet ſaith) for my Soul.</p>
               <p>Thou, moſt Glorious God! haſt done Gloriouſly, thou haſt trod down the Pride of thoſe ſpurners at thy Greatneſs, thou haſt yoaked their ſtiff Necks, for all their wild boaſting, that they go down with the moſt pompous Train, and with the beſt Company. How will they dwell in darkneſs? loſt in the Confuſion of Eternal Shame, and in the total Eclipſe of thy Favour; who with Infernal Malice did perſecute him that worſhiped thee, and deſpiſed him that ſerved thee, and hated him that loved thee? Shall ſuch at all enjoy the ſweet fruits of thy bounty? Or be remembred when thou makeſt up thy Jewels, any otherwiſe than to be condemned, and blotted out of the Book of Life? No ſurely, they ſhall ſink under the weight of their Crimes, and be buried, as well as die, in thoſe Sins wherein they choſe to live.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, what Praiſe and thanks do I not owe to my Gracious Redeemer's goodneſs? ſince thou, Lord! haſt been ſo ready to free my Shoulders from the burthen which might have broke my Back, and my Heart from thoſe Snares that would have endangered my Life or Liberty. With what exceſs of Pity haſt thou corrected the miſtakes, and prevented thoſe ſlips of my Carriage, that might have drove me down a Precipice of Deſpair?</p>
               <p>Thou, deareſt Lord! haſt waſhed out the ſpots of my Uncleanneſs,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64837:28"/>which would have made me odious to God, and Man. Thou haſt healed thoſe Wounds which were grown old and rankled by my Carnal compliances, and would have rendered my ſafety very doubtful; ſo that the Enemies of my Salvation, and of thy Glories, O God! ſhall no farther triumph over my weakneſs, nor Captivate my will that is ſo bound to thy Goodneſs.</p>
               <p>But thoſe our Enemies who would not have thee to rule over my Soul, may become like the Herbs growing on the Houſe top, that wither and come to nothing e're they can attain to any perfection of growth or Beauty. So let their vain Images be deſpiſed and neglected, as that nothing of them may be ſaved or gathered up by the meaneſt care of Men or Angels, at that great day of Harveſt, when every ones Works ſhall be made manifeſt of what ſort they are.</p>
               <p>Deal thus, Great God! with thoſe impious wretches, who are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of High-Treaſon againſt thy Majeſty, and of Felony againſt my Soul; let them fall the Victims of thy juſt Diſpleaſure, and help by their puniſhment to mitigate the Sorrows of ſuch poor wretches, as they drew into the Nets of their Sins, and ſo into joint ſufferance with themſelves: and let them glorify thy Name, even in the Fire, through that probation of thine unalterable Juſtice.</p>
               <p>In the World let them meet with no ſucceſs, until they Repent; let them haſt away like Shadows of the Night, becauſe they have loved Darkneſs, and ventured to hide themſelves from the ſight of God.</p>
               <p>Nor may they be Bleſſed by any one that paſſeth through the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of the Shadow of Death, ſo that they may be ſhut out of all hopes of Happineſs, for indeed obſtinate Sinners are like the Ground which the Lord hath Curſed; unworthy to have one Shower of good Wiſhes, or Conſolations beſtowed upon them from good men, and much more uncapable of the Dew of God's Bleſſing. But, Ah! let not my Portion be with ſuch, nor ſhut up my Life with the Bloody-minded, but impower me to reſiſt the Malice of the Evil-ones, and ſo to rely upon thy Favour, as to live under thy Protection and Cogniſance, and to be known for ever by the white Stone with a new name, even by the bleſſing of thy holieſt Name, O Lord <hi>Jeſus! Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11 (130)" type="step__Psalm">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:64837:29"/>
               <head>The eleventh Step on the eleventh PSALM of Degrees, being the 130 PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>De profundis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>O Lord how wretched, woful, lamentable is the Condition of a Sinner! who being turned into his own Enemy doth nothing but lay Ambuſhes for himſelf; while he forgets un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefully thy benefits, he becomes moſt worthleſs, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted both of Heaven and Earth! He deſerves no Manſion but in Hell. Alas, unhappy Sinner! how art thou forſaken by thy Creator, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and Comforter, even by all of thy God! and thy hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſtate is the more dreadful, being accompanied with the fearful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of Judgement. Thy Crimes bring with them unſpeakable bitterneſs, becauſe they fore-bode Eternal Torments, and thy Life is but a continual Death, by reaſon of the gnawings of Conſcience, the Horror of thy guilt, and the domineering of thine Enemies over thee.</p>
               <p>Yet for all this with the loweſt Humility that is due to the height of thy State, and to the meanneſs of mine own; while the requeſts of my Heart keep time with the Words of my Mouth, I am bold to cry aloud for Mercy, and beg thy Compaſſion, O Lord God! although thy Mercy and Compaſſion may ſeem to ſtoop too low, while they take up my Petitions unto thine Ears. And if theſe are better emploied in hearkening to the Ecchoes of thy Glories, to the Lauds of thy Saints, and to the Harmony of Heaven, yet let them not diſdain the importunity of thoſe longings after thee, which ariſe from a firm de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and a deliberate Reſolution, and addreſs themſelves to the Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool of thy Goodneſs.</p>
               <p>O Lord, I know the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is a merciful King. I know thou takeſt pleaſure in hearing the Requeſts of thy poor Creatures, eſpecially if they proceed from humble Hearts, and contrite Spirits. I know that thou art ready to put a ſtop to the Muſick of Heaven, and to give a pauſe to thine own Praiſes, rather than the Prayers of ſuch a poor Supplicant's ſhould not be liſtened to.</p>
               <p>Therefore Receive with grateful attention thoſe cries of mine, which bring with them the true evidences (as I truſt) of Converſion, as well as of Contrition. It is the great prerogative of thy Uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Majeſty, as to hear and determine of my guilty State; So by thy Mercy to receive my Petitions, and reprieve me from the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence paſſed on me by reaſon of my Crimes.</p>
               <p>Therefore I beg thou wouldſt not regard the number of my Sins, nor the Quality and Aggravations of them, which I will not pretend to enumerate by ſome few inſtances, becauſe thou knoweſt the minuteſt grain of my Offences. Thou haſt a particular of them all. And,</p>
               <p>Shouldeſt thou weigh our Guilt in the Ballance of thy Juſtice only,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64837:29"/>ſhouldſt thou be extreamly ſevere in thy puniſhment of what is amiſs about us, if thou ſhouldſt not in thy Diſpleaſure think upon thy pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and give this leave to Plead while the other arraigns; O Lord, who might abide thy preſence, or ſtand before thee in Judgment? The brighteſt Angels are not pure in reſpect of thee, and the moſt Holy would ſcarce be ſafe! Where then ſhould the Wickekd and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner appear, but in the bottomleſs Pit of Deſtruction? Had thy Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom thought good to have ſet thee only upon the Correction of our failings, the World it ſelf, as well as we, had been long ſince buried in the Cinders of our laſt Funerals; and wholly burnt up with the Fire of thy juſt Diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>But ſince thou haſt ſet thy Pity and Good-will, thy Son and thy Spirit, as better Advocates between thy own Purities and thy Creatures Frailties, than Mans weakned Nature or worſe Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties could be: for we all are too apt to ſet theſe on pleading for us, as being ever near us, yet, Ah! let us beſeech thee rather to liſten to the others in our behalf, hearken to that chiefeſt Councellor of thy ſelf and us, the moſt holy, and gracious <hi>Paraclete;</hi> and hear thy Son Interceding for us Wretches, more freely than we hear him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing of us.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Continue the incomparable Acts of thy Mercy, and exerciſe the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed proofs of thy goodneſs towards us, with the merits of Chriſt's precious Blood waſh out my ſpots, with the floods of my Tears quench the fire of my Luſts, that I may not be found the Heir of Wrath, or Child of the Devil.</p>
               <p>For indeed the true Repentance of a Sinner is the ſole effect of thy Bounty. Man that is now made up of nothing but the mud of Earthly Debauches, cannot ſo little as look up to Heaven (with the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, though he look no higher than the Clod he ſtands on) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thy ſpecial influencing aid. But this Ray thou haſt promiſed by Ten thouſand ſolemn atteſtations, and 'tis the Light of Mankind which thou haſt afforded, that it might light every one coming into the World. Saints and Prophets have born witneſs that thou art the God of Sinnes, if Penitent; thou art the Redeemer of the moſt vile and miſerable when they truely return to their Father's embraces.</p>
               <p>Let it then be an Addition to thy Glories, that thou haſt more of Pity, than I have of Provocation, and that thou yet retaineſt better Diſpoſitions to pardon Sins, than I have Inclinations to commit them. Through the exceſs of thy Goodneſs, thou haſt bounded thy own ſelf, and given leſs to thy Power and Juſtice than it might have challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and therefore have I long waited for thy Salvation, O Lord.</p>
               <p>I have endured the Stings of delay while I looked for thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and ſighed for the effects thereof; and I muſt avert my Labour hath not been in vain, for I have found the Hopes thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt me, to be anſwered; thy Word concerning me to be true and good; and thy promiſes to be performed.</p>
               <p>They may be left to their own deceivings; who wait upon the vanity of the world, and build their expectations on mortal aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. My Heart being fixed on the verity of thy Covenant, on the certainty of thy Promiſes, on the Anchor of a lively Hope, ſecures it ſelf of meeting with ſuch favour as is inſeparable from thy Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:64837:30"/>
               <p>For my own part, I am guilty of a Thouſand Crimes, nor is there any thing in me but Filth, and Frailty.</p>
               <p>I have triumphed in my Vices, as if I had liberty to commit them, and not to overcome them, even while I denied my betters the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of reprending them.</p>
               <p>Inſtead of abaſing my ſelf to the Duſt, (that Principle of my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) I have dared to contend with Omnipotence Death and Hell have been imagined Dreams and Phantaſms, only to ſcare the ſimple; and not to be Inſtruments of thine anger, to ſcourge the guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>But yet my Soul doth humbly now ſuppoſe it ſelf an Object, not leſs proper for thy incomprehenſible Mercy, becauſe of its infinite Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs, and will rely only upon that Mercy of thine, ſince it is worſe than Folly to truſt in any thing elſe.</p>
               <p>He that doth place his hopes under the protection of great men, doth but paſs away his Liberty into the Hands of Tyrants. He that founds his ſecurity on the Commonweal's, builds up his Comforts on great Improbabilities. He that counts Wealth the Mine of all Happineſs, is not acquainted with the Wheel of <hi>Fortune;</hi> he that ſooths himſelf with pleaſures in worldly Knowledge, knows not enough the weakneſs and incertainty of our Underſtandings, as well as of all intelligible Subjects; and whoſoever preſumes upon his own Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits let him call to mind from whence he came, and whither he muſt return; being liable to Myriads of Infirmities, and to more than a ſingle Death.</p>
               <p>Friends themſelves, and Health, (the beſt of humane enjoyments) are in this point like Honours, Riches, and other mortal entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, very ſhort and tranſient, under the influences of a changing ſtate, ſubject to alterations from our own age; as much as from the malice of our Enemies.</p>
               <p>Therefore, O Mortals! caſt your Anchor on no other ſecurity but on my God; there is no Rock like him, as I have experienced. He can Love us freely, and Defend us fully, he doth heal our Infirmities, and makes up our Loſſes, he protects our Weakneſs, and ſuccors our want.</p>
               <p>Where he aſſociates, there it is that Felicity both Roots and Flowers; To him let us have recourſe every Watch of the Night, and every Minute of the Day. To him let us offer up both our Lives and Deaths, the Beginning, and Accompliſhment of all our Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings.</p>
               <p>For, he that is all Goodneſs, hath no other Scope but our Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.<note place="margin">Deut. 32.4.</note> By how much the more our humane Ignorance tempts us out of the Road to Heaven, by ſo much the more his Pity ſtrives to lead us the right way, and to keep us in it.</p>
               <p>For all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> univerſal Impiety weaves a Spider's Webb in every ones Manſion;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.28.</note> and Pride heaps up Mountains of Guilt to defy Heaven; while Avarice ſcrapes up Dirt to make an Idol of it, and Laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs diſſolves its own pleaſure by exceſs: though Gluttony returns often with the Dog, and Idleneſs looks after no good, nor Anger meets with any thing but Precipices.</p>
               <p>Yet for all theſe the goodneſs of God abides continually, and is not diſcouraged by our Unworthineſs, (when even this is aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64837:30"/>by his Love) but ſtrives the rather to appear ſtill as far above our Vileneſs, and beyond our Merits, as the Heavens are diſtanced from the loweſt Earth.</p>
               <p>And, ſhall I not fly to this City of Refuge, when purſued by a many ful-mouth'd Sins, that cry aloud for Vengeance? the Diſeaſes and Corruptions of my Nature, and Condition, are not ſo inveterate, but there is Balm in <hi>Gilead,</hi> and a Phyſician there, who can eaſe them.</p>
               <p>My Wounds, though feſtered by long and evil Habits, are not gangrened by Deſpair, nor is thy Hand ſhrunk up into thy Boſom, but thou wilt put it forth to reach me a Cure. Thy Remedies, O Lord! are always ready as thy mind to recover us and thou art ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver weary of well doing.</p>
               <p>Thou alone canſt reduce me into a ſtate of doing better than I have done, Thou alone canſt pour the Oyle and Wine into my Hurts, and bear the Charges of my Recovery. Lord! lay down the price of this, and give Bail for me thy Inſoluble Debtor.</p>
               <p>As thou didſt upon the curſed Tree Redeem thy <hi>Iſrael</hi> from trouble, ſo let the Merits of thy bitter Paſſion be the powerful means of my deliverance from the ſlaveries of Sin, that I may ſerve thee without baſe Fear, without any great Diſeaſe, or Diſguſt, or Luke-warm in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference.</p>
               <p>It muſt be the heat of thy Love which can diſſipate ſuch bad Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers of my Soul, as have brought an Ague upon my Devotion, and a Plague upon my Heart. Lord! ſee me ſet right again, by the health of thy Countenance; when I am made whole, ſee that I Sin not again, leſt worſe things fall upon me. But aſſure the whole reſidue of my time, by ſuch a juſt and ſevere Repentance, (for my paſt Infirmities) as that I may never relapſe into them, nor thou ſtrive with me, who have contended too long with thee: But crowning the greatneſs of thy Glories, by the Pardon of my greateſt Sins, thou mayeſt give me leave to rely wholly on thy ſweet Compaſſion, till I may take Harbour in a Courſe of Sanctity, in the ſtate of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and at laſt, in a full and perfect Redemption. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12 (131)" type="step__Psalm">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:64837:31"/>
               <head>The twelfth Step on the twelfth PSALM of Degrees, being the 131 PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Domine, non eſt exaltatum Cor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>O Lord! I perceive the greateſt Enemy of Mankind leaves no means un-attempted whereby he may draw us out of thy bleſſed way. Sometimes with proſperous Succeſs, and ſometimes with earthly Grandeurs, he well-nigh maſters ſuch (to their Eternal Ruine) as he durſt not aſſail by Croſſes, or by Want.</p>
               <p>At other times, when neither fair means nor foul will do his Work, he takes a ſtranger courſe, and repreſents to thoſe too good Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (which we ordinarily have of our ſelves) a long Bead-roll of Religious Performances, that wee Priding our ſelves in our own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings might infect them, and arrogate that to our own merit, which is wholly due to thy goodneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ariſtot.</hi> in Eth. <hi>1.4.</hi> &amp; <hi>4.3.</hi> inquit, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ita fecrunt Optimi Gentium (Stotcorum ſcilicet &amp; Epicuraeorum) qui dixerunt. Nos ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aequat Victoria Caelo, immo &amp; ipſe Philoſophorum &amp; <hi>Romanorum</hi> Imperator, <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> erat famae ſuae curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſiſſimus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>The Beſt men of all are too much addicted to this Sacrilege; and few there are, alaſs! who are ſo well bred in Humility, as not to like their own Reputation, or not to covet Glory here, no leſs than above.</p>
               <p>Who doth not think too well or too much of his Service, if it appear faithful to God, and Charitable to others? while he is pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in Adverſity, and temperate in all his Deſires; Is he not apt to be exalted above meaſure?</p>
               <p>Therefore while I purpoſe with my ſelf to avoid the Pride and Pomps of the World, and to give my ſelf up wholly to the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy Commands, let not my Heart applaud it ſelf in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, but ſo turn mine Eyes to thy Teſtimonies, that they may not cauſe, nor diſcover any Vain-glory about me.</p>
               <p>Give me ſuch a likeneſs to my <hi>Jeſus,</hi> ſuch a lowlineſs of Spirit, as to referr all things duely to thy bounty, and nothing to my Power or Merit.</p>
               <p>And as by the exceſſes of undeſerved loving-kindneſs, thou haſt advantaged my Birth with the Characters of Illuſtrious Parentage. Thou haſt enriched my Well-being with many temporal Honours, and Privileges above others: ſo grant that I may not exceed the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of my Duty, nor preſume to take thy Praiſes to my ſelf.</p>
               <p>For my Birth (whether high or low) was not my choice, but thy good Will, and I can no more ſecure my Life, than I could at firſt chuſe it. For my Death ſhall come as my Life did, when it ſhall pleaſe thee to ſend it; and that too, ſhall pull off all diſguiſes; leaving me naked, as from my Mothers Womb, and in no better a condition
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64837:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>than the pooreſt Mortal. And this the Princely <hi>Job</hi> taught both him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and us, when humbled to the very Dunghill.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 1.20, 21.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Worldly Honours are deſigned by thy good Providence to be Spurs to our Vertue, while we ride through the ſhort Stages of this frail Life, and they ſhould be looked on as ſtreams iſſuing from thee their Fountain; ſo that when we grow proud of them we kick a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, and make brutiſh returns of Ingratefulneſs to thy ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial favours.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Humane Learning (which is meer ignorance in reſpect of thy knowledg) is an Oyntment that is fly-blown, corrupt and unſavoury; when the Philoſopher is ſuch a Fool as to glory in his Wiſdom.</p>
               <p>Therefore entertain my notions, good Lord! within the compaſs of a juſt moderation, that they may not boil over with conceit, or opinion; nor build Caſtles in the Air, (like <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s Eagles) ſoaring above the proper reach of my own capacities.</p>
               <p>Give me, I beſeech thee, an exact and ſober underſtanding of my ſelf, that Pride may have nothing to do within me, nor without. But that Humility may take its right place about me, and not be wrongfully ejected by Worldly Circumſtances.</p>
               <p>Though Titles, Wealth, and Friends, may difference me from others. Gracious Father! I deſire that my beſt skill may be uſed in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodating me to others, in the levelling my conceit of my ſelf to him that hath the meaneſt thoughts of me; while I confeſs my ſelf as miſerable a Sinner as mortal a Creature, as the moſt abject wretch in the World can be.</p>
               <p>If I ſtrive for Precedence, let it be only as Chriſt's Diſciples did, to be nearer to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> to out-ſtrip others in Prayer, and Faſting, and ſuch like Acts of Piety as may prove, that I have drank of his Cup of Grace.</p>
               <p>I would diveſt my ſelf of all ſuch habits as like falſe Glaſſes render me bigger than the Life, and count my beſt efforts for thee to be nothing in compariſon of what thou haſt done me, dear Saviour! and thus will I traffick for true Glory, by getting all the Praiſe and Honour which I can for thee, till I come into the Harbour of thy Eternal Grace, and Goodneſs.</p>
               <p>Should I indulge the Pride of my Nature, I ſhould loſe the pleaſure of thy Love. For Pride is a Sin ſo hainous as that it could tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form an Angel, and throw him out of Heaven, and Man out of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice, for both their High-Treaſons againſt thy Majeſty; whereas Humility is the eldeſt Siſter of the Graces, and the firſt born of the Beatitudes, having promiſes like the Fifth Commandment, both for this Life and a better; and although Haughtineſs of Temper is one of the Goads of Nature which puſhes Man forward (ſince he was made with expectation of Dominion) yet Lord! abaſe this Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering humour, leaſt Pride, that is the Queen of Vice, and firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Child of Sin, and the immediate Succeſſor of Wrath, and Vengeance, leſt Pride, I ſay, ſhould get the better of that Lowlineſs, I would ſtill keep in my Soul for the better imitation of my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</p>
               <p>When I conſider how that dangerous forementioned Crime hath armed Legions of Angels to revenge it; <q>I fear leſt it ſhould make me be (not like <hi>David</hi> in this <hi>Pſalm</hi>) but like an unhappy Child of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64837:32"/>
                     <hi>Rachel,</hi> ſnatched away from the Boſom of my deareſt Parent, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the ſweet and precious Milk of thy Word; or of any Spiritual refreſhment.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But for all Humility is ſo needful, (as the Mother of Vertues) yet a man ſhould not rely upon the brittle ſtaff of the beſt natural performances, even in the very Duty of meekneſs, and lowlineſs of Mind. Since our Salvation is ſecured by thy goodneſs, and in our holieſt Operations there is no Merit to Redeem us from Sin, or to entail thy Graces on us, upon thee alone we muſt ground our hopes; from thee onely ſprings our Happineſs, by thy good pleaſure Eternity is conſigned to us.</p>
               <p>He that ſets his Heart on Riches, what doth he, but rear up Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles, whereon his Soul may be tempted, and his Life indangered? Gold is ſaid to be Devoted to <hi>Pluto,</hi> becauſe he that truſts therein can promiſe himſelf nothing at the laſt but the lowermoſt Pit. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, are rather the Gifts of Fortune than of Merit, and abandon, men uſually at the approach of Calamities. Friends are gained by intereſt, and loſt by Death, if not by ſome odd Caſualty before. Health is ſhort and fleeting, made ſo by change of Diet, Air, and every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Soul or Body. In fine,</p>
               <p>All mortal Hopes and Joyes are liable to the Tempeſts of innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Accidents.</p>
               <p>Thou onely, Almighty Lord! art He that changeſt not, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore art my ſafe Anchor-hold, and the Rock of my Hope.</p>
               <p>In thee Devout Souls pitch their abſolute truſt, becauſe there is no time wherein thou art not able, willing, and ready to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date them with Mercies, and with thine infinite Beneficence. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13 (132)" type="step__Psalm">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:64837:32"/>
               <head>The thirteenth Step on the thirteenth PSALM of Degrees, being the 132 PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Memento Domine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>O Gracious Lord! Look with the Eyes of thine infinite com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion upon a wretched Sinner, and remember that I am thy Servant, I am thy Servant, and the Son of thy Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid; let me refuge my ſelf now at thine Altars, though I have been ſuch an Idolater, as to worſhip moſt of the World's Naughtineſs.</p>
               <p>I have adored earthly pleaſures, yet deny me not thy favourable protection, look not upon me as on ſuch an huge offender (who hath warred againſt thy Holineſs, by heaps upon heaps of vain aſpiring thoughts.) But,</p>
               <p>Conſider me as thy Creature, as a penitent and humble Convert, who may be a fit Object for thy mighty Compaſſion, through the ſenſe I have at preſent of my Vileneſs. This is great, ſince I have been Impotent, Impious, nay Sacrilegious.</p>
               <p>My Tongue hath dared to profane thy ſacred Attributes. My Hands have not ſpared the Blood or Honour of others, my Heart hath pitched its delight among brutiſh and ſenſual paſtimes, even ſuch as have been repugnant to thy laws, and to thoſe of Humanity.</p>
               <p>But now that by my Converſion thou mayeſt be glorified; Haſt thou not obliged thy ſelf by the truth of thy promiſes, to receive ſuch guilty ones as are <hi>Weary and heavy laden?</hi> becauſe thou art a God of Mercy, and <hi>There is more joy in Heaven for one Sinner that Repents, than for Ninety and nine ſuch Righteous perſons, as think with the</hi> Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, <hi>they need no Repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know mine Eyes have been treacherous Scouts to my Soul. I know mine Ears have been like the Adder's, and deaf to thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and to every good Exhortation, though open to the Whiſpers of a lying World. The motions of my outward man, like thoſe of my inward, have been but to hurry me to ruine. I know my Heart hath been moſt vain in its deſires, blind in its appetites, mad in that indulging of them: yet I rely upon thy Pity, and deſpair not of thy Forgiveneſs.</p>
               <p>As thou didſt comply with the Vehement ſtruglings of <hi>Jacob</hi> for a Bleſſing, when he had cauſe enough to fear his own weakneſs; ſo do thou afford me thy Guidance and Protection, that I may not only begin well to turne towards Thee, but that I may go on from Strength to Strength to meet Thee, and if thy Grace ſo forward my Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, I ſhall not doubt of performing what I have promiſed, (that is) to give Thee all which the devouteſt Soul can offer.</p>
               <p>My Heart would have no other place to recreate its affections in, but in the Preſence-Chamber of thy Love.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:64837:33"/>
               <p>What do the richeſt Marbles ſignify (though they have often ſweat under the Tools of Cunning Workmen, for the adorning of ſome Cloſet for me) if my Rocky Heart be not broke by thy divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts? The Battels wrought in Tapiſtry, which hide the nakedneſs of my Walls, do ſilently upbraid my Vanity, Hypocriſy, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, and Quarrels that engage my Soul by many differing Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; all which make ſpoil of my Reaſon, inſtead of ſerving her.</p>
               <p>While the Eye Tries it ſelf, through a long Proſpect of Apartments, wherein much skill might be likewiſe tired by its Obſervations of Ten thouſand Rarities: even there my Remembrance offers me an Inventory of my faults, which ſeem deſperate enough to ſnatch the Golden Scepter of thy goodneſs, even out of thy Hand, and to cut me off from all hopes of Mercy.</p>
               <p>Yet Lord! caſt me out of doors, let me be onely covered with the Canopy of Heaven; take away, not onely my Fineneſs and Superflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but my Eaſe and Proſperity: nay, even my Houſes and Lands, my other Comforts, and Health too, from me, rather than deny me thy Grace, for what greater Bleſſing can I beg than it?</p>
               <p>The Favours of Princes are lightnings that blind us with their Splendor. Riches and Beauty corrupt daily; They ſeemingly depend upon ſtrange uncertain accidents.</p>
               <p>Power and Honours are no leſs dangerous than Elevating: But the poſſeſſion of thy Favour is a boundleſs Gulf of Happineſs. What Golden Shours of ineffable ſweetneſs are pour'd into their breaſts who enjoy the priviledg thereof?</p>
               <p>Wherefore although I ſhould deny Sleep to mine Eyes, and Slumber to their Lids, for thy ſake, O God! yet even by ſuch actions I ſhould meet with the greater Repoſe: nay, with that unſpeakable Quiet, and ſerenity of thy beloved and choſen People.</p>
               <p>So that I deſire not that any part of me ſhould find Eaſe and Reſt, without a ſenſibility of thy Grace, and a reſpect to thy Will.</p>
               <p>All my Bones ſhall ſay, <hi>Lord! Who is like thee?</hi> and as thou haſt obliged, ſo do thou unite all my diſorderly affections: Bind them with the Cords of Divine Love unto thine Altars; that they may not be undone by the diſſoluteneſs of this Age; ſtrengthen my Weakneſs, encourage my Reſolutions to get the better of my Frailties, and of my Inconſtancy, leaſt I fall into every Temptation of Sin, or Snare of the Devil. I ſeek no farther ſecurity than thy Favour, no fairer Boon than thy Grace, no fuller Bliſs than thy Boſom affords.</p>
               <p>But to obtain theſe, Lord! there is requiſite a more intire Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to thy Will, a continued Repentance of my Tranſgreſſions, and a reſolution fixed rather upon dying than offending Thee any more.</p>
               <p>And is not this Diſpoſition the <hi>Ephratah</hi> mentioned, wherein we may find <hi>Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surely he that can behave himſelf Righteouſly, Soberly, and Holily towards the World, Himſelf, and Satan, need not doubt but that he may ſee God's Face, and Live alſo.</p>
               <p>For God is good, and doth good to all ſuch as keep his Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and walk in his wayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Where there is any goodneſs, he will not be a far off, Where there is any true Piety there is God at hand: for he loves to Crown his own Gifts, and to Glorify his own Graces, and to have his
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:64837:33"/>delights with the Sons of Men, when theſe are willing to become the Sons of God, by coming to his onely begotten <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This I have found by experience; and how great is my Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to thee, moſt dear Redeemer! who would ſuffer thy ſelf to be found in the ſharp Covert of my Breaſt, in that ſtrong Wood, where Sin left none of the Cedars of God (which are full of Sap) but only a few Shrubs of impotent affections, which are ſo full of Briars, and Aſperities, as that they oppoſed thy entrance into my Soul, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented Thee with nothing, but another Crown of Thorns.</p>
               <p>Yet ſince I have not onely heard of Thee with the Hearing of the Ear, but my other Senſes have been ſufficient Witneſſes of thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable Kindneſs, and of thy Addreſſes to me, that I might find thee. O that I may find ſuch favour in thy ſight, as to have a ſight ſtill of thy Favour! Let my Worſhipping of Thee keep ſome meaſure with thy Working upon me, that I may be renewed day by day.</p>
               <p>Undreſs my Soul of all ſuch mean Garbs, and ſinful Compliances, as will render it uncomly or unfit for thy ſight. This Soul, dear Lord! of which thou wouldeſt be the Maker and Redeemer alſo; doth not more triumph in thy preſent bounty than it is afraid to forfeit it. Therefore,</p>
               <p>Come now, and take up thy abode therein: Shall my Sins keep Thee knocking at the Door? No, deareſt Lord! come in; my Lord come in while I am ready (as thy Spouſe ſhould always be) to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Thee my beloved Bridegroom.</p>
               <p>What Sinners need deſpair of Mercy, while a Saviour Invites, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats, and even pulls them by force out of the <hi>Sodom</hi> of their Sins and dangers, unto a Repentance which may bring them to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? And,</p>
               <p>How eaſily is Heaven opened by the Tears of Contrition? How pleaſed is the Divine Pity at ſuch Tears?</p>
               <p>Theſe Showers return again upon the Earth with Peace to it, Good will to Men, they bring God Glory, and his Glory to us, they cauſe Heaven's Jubile, and the Angels Triumph, becauſe the Return of a Sinner is the moſt grateful Tribute that the Creature can offer to its Creator, and God delights himſelf in the Election of ſuch Inſtruments as are changed from Veſſels of diſhonour, and fitted for his ſervice by Converſion: Since the procurement of his Grace and Favour is not the Fruit of our Merit, but of his own Goodneſs.</p>
               <p>For all we may Weep, Sigh, Pray, Faſt, make Reſtitution, give Almes, reſolve againſt Sin, and mortify our Paſſions, and bridle our Affections, and our corrupt Appetites, in ſome decent manner; yet our Nature hath many Frailties, and renders our beſt deeds ſo imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as without the exceſs of thy Compaſſion, without the Merits of Chriſt's ſufferings we ſhould ſtill be found ſuch wicked and unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Servants, as to have no more hope than worth in our beſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances.</p>
               <p>On therefore, O my Soul! and (for all thy former demerits) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by the devouteſt applications of God's Grace to be raiſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Mount <hi>Sion:</hi> and to be made thy ſelf a Temple, an Habitation for the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> where thy Lord himſelf may delight to dwell; thou canſt not aſpire to more Happineſs than to be a Manſion for his Son, and Spirit.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:64837:34"/>
               <p>Therefore know the way of truth, and walk in it, make right paths for thy Feet, ſince they that wander through Ignorance, are loſt or confounded by their own darkneſs.</p>
               <p>Let thy Knowledg, and thy Zeal prevent thy ſelf, and other Sinners too, from rejoicing in their own Errors; by due Auſterities detourn them from their Perverſeneſs. By good Counſel aſſiſt others in their affairs, and ſuccor them in their affliction. With the Shield of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience break through the thickeſt Ranks of thine Adverſaries, and overcome them by thy Charity. Receiving Injuries without being galled by them, without retorting ſuch venomed Artillery, but rather pray for Enemies, do good to ſuch as hate and perſecute, and then thou ſhalt find (as the Hoſpitable King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did) that God ſhall be on thy ſide,<note place="margin">2 King. 6.16, 23.</note> and more for thee than againſt thee.</p>
               <p>But woe to that Soul that by its diſ-belief of God's Word hath treſpaſſed ſo hainouſly, as to drive away God's Love that was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to leave it. Woe to that Soul which becomes blind by its profane Obſtinacy, in ſuch a manner as to make it ſelf an Object of God's Scorn and deriſion then, when it might be the Object of his Love and Delight!</p>
               <p>No Words, no Thought can exemplify the direful miſeries of that State, which becomes ſo infinitely wretched as not onely to be left Sentenced by God, but juſtly Puniſhed and Condemned: <q>Nay, Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and derided and inſtead of being pitied by the unſpeakable Bowels of an Heavenly Father, (for its perpetual loſs and torment) have the Furnace of Hell made ſeven times hotter, by the deriſion of God and holy Angels, as if they rejoyced, and took pleaſure in the Pains of the Damned: while they adore and praiſe the Juſtice, and Holineſs of God, in giving to each one his due. And,</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Thus it comes to paſs, as there is Joy in Heaven for the converſion of a Penitent; ſo there may be Joy too there, for the eternal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and deſerved Ruine of an un-repenting and obſtinate Offender.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>As we may infer from the words of Divine Wiſdom ſpoken in the Firſt Chapter of <hi>Proverbs</hi> from the <hi>24th</hi> Verſ. to the end of that Chapter.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24.</note>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>So that of all thoſe many Showers of Grace that God ſo plentifully and continually ſends down, in theſe days of our Viſitation; there will not be one drop left to cool the tongue of a <hi>Dives,</hi> when he may be ſweltring in perpetual Flames.</q> All that which might have nouriſhed and feaſted the Soul; turns to its Poyſon, and infects it more with the Diſeaſe and Nature of the Devils.</p>
               <p>But on the other ſide, <q>How bleſſed is the choice Spirit which laying hold on the Promiſe, and obeying the Precepts of its God, thrives ſo wonderfully under his gracious Bleſſing,<note place="margin">Dan. 4.12, 13.</note> as to be fruitful notwithſtanding its height, and out of danger of falling.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>No evil Spirit ſhall have power to caſt it down ſince it is watched by an Angel, and an Holy one receiving the Birds of Paradice within its Arms.</q>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord! What Solace, and what Happineſs may I not ſecure to my ſelf, if I have the favour of thy good Will and Protection? for thou doſt not baffle the hopes of ſuch as anchor themſelves upon the Rock <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> thou doſt not break the Knees that are bowed down, or bruiſed in their frequent Devotion before thee.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:64837:34"/>
               <p>Thou doſt not weary our Expectations, neither doſt thou hate our Prayers or our Perſons: but thou loveſt thy Creature, yet not his Sin, Thou heareſt his requeſts by Chriſt's Interceſſions.</p>
               <p>Thy Promiſes (not blended with ſelf-intereſt) are never ſubject to alteration, as men's are too much. Thine immenſe bounty is the Parent of thy good Will to Mankind; and is unchangeable, becauſe exempt both from Jealouſy and Fear. Thy wiſeſt Providence leades all our operations through ſeveral amazing Labyrinths to moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ends, and many times far otherwiſe than we deſigned them.</p>
               <p>Thy Mercy, that is ſo tender as to be wrought on by a Mortal's Sigh or Tear, calls every Sinner, watches, and waits his leiſure (as it were) accepts and welcoms him almoſt at any time, after it hath provided the Feſtival too for his Cheer, without any Contribution, or Charges of the Gueſt.</p>
               <p>Thy Wiſdom is a depth paſt fathoming too, and therein like, (though tranſcending our Demerits) it knows (though we do not) always who are thine, and can work good and Glory out of the worſt of man's Miſery, and the Devils Malice.</p>
               <p>O that this fore-praiſed Wiſdom, and Love of thine, may work theſe following Effects.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let the one ſubdue thoſe Adverſaries of thy Glory, and my Good, who oppoſe themſelves to my thorough Converſion, Tyrannizing over my Will, and perverting the devout Affections that now and then warm my Heart.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let the other enrich my Soul with Grace. As <hi>David</hi> was bleſſed in thy Love, and became an Illuſtrious Inſtrument for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing thy Glory: So I may be inſtalled for ever with the tokens of thy Favour, and with the ornaments of thy meek and holy Spirit.</p>
               <p>I ſee the World arrayed with Vanity, and dawbed over with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, its ſweets (like too hot perfumes) ſtrongly aſſault the weakneſs of our ſenſes, and the ſoftneſs of my Conſtitution diſcover the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of the Fleſh againſt the Spirit.</p>
               <p>I fear my Levity, and inconſideration will lay me open to the inveiglements of my ſubtileſt Foes. And ſhall I not pray then againſt their wickedneſs? that thou wouldeſt fruſtrate their attempts againſt me, and confound their Devices. Leaſt I be confounded, who repair to thy holieſt Sanctuary for Protection.</p>
               <p>Save me then, O Lord! who Renouncing the Devil and his Works, and forſaking the Pomps and Vanities of this wicked World, and all the ſinfull Luſts of the Fleſh, would be faithful unto death, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from thee alone a Crown of Life, of Grace here, and Glory hereafter. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14 (133)" type="step__Psalm">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:64837:35"/>
               <head>The fourteenth Step on the fourteenth PSALM of Degrees, being the 133 PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Ecce quam bonum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>LIft up thy ſelf, O my Soul! and be thou raiſed up from the burthen of my Sins, unto the Throne of the Moſt High: for though God be the abſolute diſpenſer of his own Grace, yet he loves to have it coveted, and looked after by Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, ſince his delights are placed amongſt us. Be ſure not to leave his preſence; wander no more like a <hi>Cain</hi> from his ſight: for although nothing be covered from his inſpection, yet as he that travels far Northward baniſhes himſelf from the Sun's power, and will not be advantaged by his heat, ſo much as if he ſtayed near the place where the Sun makes his Bed at Noon: So neither can he receive the warmeſt influences of Gods Favour, who departs from it, like an offending <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore, O my Soul! Renounce thy Worldly affections altogether, and know that whoſoever leaves his Heart to be entrapped by the fair ſemblances of Earthly Toys, may loſe his ſhare in an Eternity of Glory, while he embraces nothing but a Cloud, and catches unhappily at a Shadow.</p>
               <p>Alas! all Sublunary things are too ſlight to be compared with the pleaſures at God's Right-hand. What is moſt compleat here is ever aſſailed by its contraries, and what appears moſt Gygantick, or mighty, is but the greater Impoſture, cheating our apprehenſion by the caſt of a huge Shadow.</p>
               <p>That which is ſweeteſt to our Senſes is incompaſſed with the moſt ſtings, as our lovelieſt Roſes have the ſharpeſt prickles; here is no Hony but what is ſcoured with Wormwood, and the whole courſe of our Lives is but a <hi>L'ambigue,</hi> a ſtrange Hotchpotch of Good and Evil. But in God, in God alone is found true Good, and perfect Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs.</p>
               <p>Many things that are uſeful are not pleaſant, and many pleaſant things are noxious. Faſting, Abſtinence, and large Alms-deeds en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich the Mind, mortify the Paſſions, while they ſeem to impair our Worldly Concernments.</p>
               <p>On the contrary, the ſatisfaction of ſenſuality may careſſe the Body, but they torture the Soul. In God alone meets that Profit and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which conſtitute the chief Good. Therefore,</p>
               <p>O my Soul! with fervent Devotion, ſincere Converſion, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled Reſolution, be fixed to thy Redeemer, and enjoy ſuch bliſs as is made over to thoſe who are acquainted with God's Mind, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to his Commands.</p>
               <p>How unhappy are the Scorners of ſuch acquaintance, and Union with God; Sit not thou in their place, if thou meaneſt to be happy:
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:64837:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>for they have took leave of their Felicity, they have ſhook hands with Faith, and Charity; they are Eclipſed from the Beams of the Sun of Righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>Yet let thoſe ſottiſh Animals inform me (if they can) why the bright Planet of the Day is ſo welcom to univerſal Nature? Why the ſending forth its Light and Heat draws up their Eyes, and the Faculties of the whole World, as it were, to the admiration of it ſelf? Why are the four Elements ſo needful, if they be not Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative and aſſiſtant to every Body? and is not the Maker of theſe much more wonderful, as much more neceſſary to us all?</p>
               <p>He that will lean to his own imaginations, makes them his Idols; and forfeits the Inheritance, that might be had by Communion with God. But he that with a right affection, and with Filial Reverence binds up all Cravings within the good pleaſure, and will of God, may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive all the Joys that can be handed to him by a Deity, for ſuch an Obſervance. Such Union of a Soul to Chriſt, is more ſweet and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to Heaven, than was that holy Oyle which the High-prieſts onely were to make and uſe.</p>
               <p>And as the Heavenly dew that falls upon the Hills of <hi>Hermon,</hi> and of <hi>Sion,</hi> brings Fruitfullneſs to their Rocks, and Health to their Inhabitants, ſo the Largeſſes of the Divine Bounty, many ways ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage all ſuch as are united to a Saviour, and to one another by a copious Charity.</p>
               <p>The Dew comes down ſilently from Heaven, and waters the Earth, being nouriſhing, and medicinal: and ſuch a Celeſtial thing is Love and Concord, Curing all the Diſeaſes of the Mind.</p>
               <p>It ſoftens the very Marbles of a proud <hi>Niobe,</hi> improves the ſterile bottom of Good-works; ſweetens the Aſperities of Contrition, and prevents the withering of our Hopes.</p>
               <p>Send down this precious Dew upon my Soul, O Lord! as thou didſt another on the Fleece of <hi>Gideon,</hi> that being over-ſhadowed by thy Love, I may never Divorce my ſelf again from it, but value my affections (as thou doſt) even as Faculties more conſiderable than are all thoſe earthly Objects upon which they have been too often caſt away: but ſince Mundanities are ſo imperfect Comforts, &amp; ſo vaniſhing; they ſhould be deſpicable. And I would devote my Heart altogether to thoſe Joys of thine, which are Eternal.</p>
               <p>Guard it therefore with a generous Fortitude to reſiſt all the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the Devil, to diſarm all my Senſes, to defeat all my Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, from ever having any more Power to make me rebel againſt thy Goodneſs. And, Lord! command all the Forces of my Soul to concur in the deſires of thy Mercy, in the doing thy Will, in the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying thy Greatneſs; ſo ſhall I be ſecure of thy Grace here, and of thy Glory hereafter. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15 (134)" type="step__Psalm">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:64837:36"/>
               <head>The fifteenth Step on the fifteenth PSALM of Degrees, being the 134 PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Ecce nunc benedicite.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>O My Soul! how art thou engaged by the Mercies of thy Creator to reinforce thy Powers for the ſetting forth his Praiſe; Now lay the Top-ſtone of thy Happineſs in the bleſſing of thy dear Redeemer; who hath ſuffered thee to get up thus near unto him, and to free thee from Sin, hath ſhewed the mighty skill of his Mercy in diverſe manners.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> In the delivering thee from the perils of Infidelity and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> In giving thee the due confidence thou oughteſt to have in his Goodneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> In letting thee ſee how all true pleaſures flow from him, who is all Love and Kindneſs.</p>
               <p>Hath he enriched thee with the Ornaments of Hope? Hath he built thee upon the Groundwork of Charity, with the ſtrength of a right Faith? Hath he taught thee the fear of the Lord, and the reſpect due to his Command? Hath he ſhewed thee the Conſequence of Holy Sorrow, Meekneſs, and Exinanition? and at laſt invited thee to all Happineſs, by a perfect union to Himſelf? And,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Art thou not inaugurated with a Crown of Privileges? Art thou not wholly ſubdued to God, and overcome by ſuch powerful Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to confeſs, that Religion muſt needs be thy greateſt advantage, and higheſt advancement alſo?</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then forget not thy ſelf ſo much as not to exalt his Merits, and bleſs his Mercy, and declare what he hath done for thee, as Loudly, as Plainly, as Continually, as 'tis poſſible for thee to do.</p>
               <p>If thou ſlipp the time for theſe requiſite performances, (and which is thy time but the preſent?) It will look like an Act of Ingratitude, and an effect of Obduration.</p>
               <p>To the wicked, ſaith God, <hi>What haſt thou to do to take my Name in thy Mouth, ſince thou hateſt to be reformed.</hi> O Lord! thou wilt have none of their Commendations, who indeed are unworthy to utter thy holieſt Name, being thy profeſſed Enemies, their Addreſſes are but like the gnaſhings of the Damned, meer Profanations, and no Worſhip of Thee.</p>
               <p>But thy Servants are the Ecchoing Trumpets of thy Goodneſs; Thou loveſt their Eulogies, whom thou haſt adorned with thy Favours, and Redeemed from the Tyranny of their Accuſer.</p>
               <p>Conſider then again and again, O my Soul! how Great! how Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible! is the Goodneſs of thy God! ſince he would Create thee after his likeneſs, and give thee Underſtanding, and Dominion over and above thy Fellow-creatures? Since he would place thee at firſt but little lower
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64837:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>than the Angels, and hereafter will promote thee even above thoſe bleſſed Spirits; ſince he would ſave thee with no leſs a Price than his Son's Blood; and make thee the chief Magazine, or Store-houſe of all the Treaſures of his Grace: ſince he would Manumitt thee by his Service, from the Tyranny of thy Senſualities, and from the Slavery of great Tranſgreſſions (which bind up <hi>Lucifer</hi> himſelf in Chains of Darkneſs.) O! do not fall (like him) again into the Hell of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, ſince thou art raiſed thus into the Favour of the Moſt High: Employ thy faculties to his Honour, elſe thou art ſuch another un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Monſter as deſerves to be entombed in the bottom of that Gulph which burns for Ever and Ever.</p>
               <p>Shew at leaſt how thou ſavoureſt the things of God, by acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of them; 'Tis true, thou canſt never render unto him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as thou haſt received, yet return thy improved Talents, and thy utmoſt abilities, or elſe thy chearful readineſs, for the owning thy ſelf Obliged, and not unkind, to the Donor.</p>
               <p>Suffer no Excuſe or Accident to put thee off from thinking of his Goodneſs, or from thanking of it.</p>
               <p>Thy Proſperity is the Iſſue of his Providence, not of thy Merit. God (ſaith the Wiſe man) enables us to get Wealth, and all good Fortune. Thy Adverſaries celebrate his Wiſdom, for by them art thou taught how he knows thy deſert, and would try thy Patience, and deals not ſo hardly by thee as he is provoked.</p>
               <p>Therefore in all Conditions ſet forth his moſt worthy Praiſe; with clean Hands, and a pure Heart lifted up by devout Expreſſions. Let us lead on our Deſires, and endeavours to ſet the Crown upon his Head, and to put the Scepter into his Hand, whoſe right it is.</p>
               <p>I mean let our Church (with that which is Triumphant) aſcribe <hi>All Honour, Power, Dominion, and Glory unto him who ſits upon the Throne, and unto the Lamb, for evermore:</hi> bleſſing God every manner of way, whereby the Creature may be ſaid to Glorify his maker. As,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> By ſpeaking of God with that Reverence which the Majeſty of his Perſon doth require.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> By living according to the Rules of Probity, that by our good actions, both our ſelves and others may think well of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> By rendering unto God the Honour due to his Name, in whatſoever condition may we be, that whether he gives or takes away, there may be no ſhipwrack of a good Conſcience, or of a chearful Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, becauſe we own our dependance not upon our ſelves but Him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> By <hi>Giving Thanks always for all things unto God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.20.</note> (as ſaith the Apoſtle) while we entertain a grateful Taſt and Remembrance of the moſt ordinary Mercy, for there is none to be looked upon as little, if we juſtly regard either God or our ſelves.</p>
               <p>NOW, moſt Gracious Lord! ſince thou haſt called up my Soul to this exalted Throne of Felicity, to this higheſt Round of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Comfort, (to wit) to the reſounding of thy Praiſes, for the efficacy of thy Favours towards a penitent Sinner: I beſeech thee, deareſt Lord! ſhower down continuall thy Gifts and Graces upon my humbled Soul, that it may be fruitful in every good Work, and ſhew no wretched marks of its former Sterility, though it Merits not the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:64837:37"/>ſmalleſt Dew of thy Bleſſing, nor the leaſt warmth of thy Love; (having ſcarce put out the fire of extravagant Luſt.) Yet ſince thou haſt founded the vaſt Machine of the Univerſe upon the empty place; Thine out-ſtretched arm can amend and ſanctify whatever is amiſs about me.</p>
               <p>Thou art both our Lord, and our God; a Maker, and Redeemer too; whoſe Operations are beyond all impoſſibilities, and thy Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits above our Deſires, eſpcially in Heavenly things, no leſs than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove our Deſerts.</p>
               <p>However, give me leave, here at laſt, to beſeech thee ſo to fit me for thine Eternal Entertainments, by a thankful Senſe, and conſtant reliſh of thy Love and Goodneſs to me here, as that I may paſs along ſafely and contentedly through the many diſquiets of this mortal Life, to the continual Praiſing, and endleſs Fruition of thee in Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>our Father which art,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="corollary">
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:64837:37"/>
            <head>A COROLLARY.</head>
            <p>HAving got up thus far by the help of others, (with aking Knees, and ſobbing Reſpirations) my Soul craves leave to pauſe and look about her, leſt theſe Aſcents become to her condition, like the <hi>Scalae Gemoniae</hi> to condemned Wretches, Degrees of Puniſhment, and ſad occaſions of more certain Ruine. Theſe lofty Mounts afford me a fair proſpect of the good Way my Thoughts ſhould take toward Heaven: But, alas! I find at the ſame time how I am groveling upon Earth, and the feet of my Affections would rather ſtep down, than go up ſo high a Hill, as that of God's Houſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore have I need of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Staff to lean upon in my infirmeſt State,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.21. <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.39, 36.</note> and to point out how few and evil the days of the years of my Pilgrimage have been, and to fathom better both God's Love and mine, that I may get up ſtill nearer the point of Life, (even in Death it ſelf) and be keeping on my Journey here, for here is not my Reſt.</p>
            <p>And as I want a <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Staff, (ſuch a help and Monitor, and Viſion, as that holy Traveller had at <hi>Bethel</hi>) ſo I deſire likewiſe that <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Ladder, which according to St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> (in his Homilies on the <hi>Pſalms</hi>) is the Exerciſe of a devout Soul, ſo employing it ſelf, as that God may come down to it, and the Soul be raiſed up to Heaven, by theſe five ſeveral Degrees or Aſcents.</p>
            <p>The firſt is a generous neglect of all outward and temporal Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> in reſpect of Heavenly ones; a forſaking of our Nets, like true Converts, and Chriſtian Diſciples,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 1.18.</note> for the attendance on the Lord <hi>Jeſus;</hi> and not only renouneing (with St. <hi>Paul</hi>) ſuch things as we counted Gain, but,</p>
            <p>Secondly, Contemning,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and even loathing the moſt admired ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual pleaſures, nay, the World it ſelf, when ſet in competition with Chriſt out Saviour:</p>
            <p>Becauſe, in the third place,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> a we ought to love nothing in compariſon of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> if we would be love by him:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.37. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10.</note> If we eſteem him not moſt amiable, we are not warmed with a right, or kindly flame of Devotion, (which implies a tranſcendent value for the adored Object of our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.) We are but <hi>Samaritans</hi> in our pretended Religion, and ſhall hardly arrive at the fourth Step,</p>
            <p>Which is a readineſs not only to be bound, but to dye for his Name:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> And this propenſity for the meeting Death it ſelf in the way to Life,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.24.</note> is
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:64837:38"/>a good Token or part of the nobleſt Mortification, which prefers God and his Sanctity before Life, nay, before Salvation, and will ſecure us from finding Death in the Errors of our Lives.</p>
            <p>Nay,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> laſtly, will ſtrengthen us to climb up to the Top-round of theſe Spiritual Exerciſes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25.</note> even to the uniting our Souls by the divineſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity unto God himſelf, who is Love and the Man that can get thither (ſaith St. <hi>John</hi>) <hi>dwells in Gods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>and God in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Five <hi>Aſcents</hi> are to be often mounted, and if in honour to the holieſt Trinity, they are thrice gone over in our youthfulleſt, in our ſtrongeſt, and in our oldeſt Age, we ſhall be perfect in our Duty by ſuch Repetitions of it, and not think the Fifteen <hi>Aſcents</hi> to <hi>God's Houſe</hi> at all too many, or too ſteep, or tireſom.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>IN the Epiſtle to the Reader, <hi>Page</hi> 1. <hi>Line</hi> 28. for <hi>quote,</hi> read <hi>Court. p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 48. read <hi>Sketch. p.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 19. for <hi>ones,</hi> read <hi>ends. l.</hi> 49. read <hi>Ite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next Epiſtle of the Author, at <hi>l.</hi> 12. inſert <hi>its. p.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 12. read <hi>to Heaven. p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 8. read <hi>perfect ones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Book, <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 7. read <hi>thee. p.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 2. read <hi>it natural, and born with us. l.</hi> 32. read <hi>or recover it.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:64837:38"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Euchariſt at Eaſter,</hi> 1657, ON THE Happy Recovery Of my Moſt Dear and Honour'd LUCINDA.</head>
            <l>ANGELS, come tune my Joys, ſince they require</l>
            <l>Notes pure and high, like thoſe which ye inſpire;</l>
            <l>Bleſt Saints of Heav'n! could ye impart your Mirth,</l>
            <l>Then might I learn to ſing of one on Earth,</l>
            <l>One, who hath not your Glory, yet your Grace;</l>
            <l>One equals you in Piety, not Place,</l>
            <l>Becauſe ſhe lives: Nor can I more expreſs</l>
            <l>To tell, what 'tis the World calls <hi>Happineſs;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And ſince ſhe lives, I pray for nothing more,</l>
            <l>But how to praiſe that help I did implore.</l>
            <l>O God (who art moſt powerful) do thou pleaſe</l>
            <l>To give me thankfulneſs, who gav'ſt her eaſe;</l>
            <l>Give ſtrength (as to her Body) to my Brain,</l>
            <l>That with her health, may Harmonize my ſtrain,</l>
            <l>And breath ſtill vigorouſly, like my paſt Fears,</l>
            <l>In Lines more numerous than were earſt my Tears;</l>
            <l>While every gladſome Verſe records at once</l>
            <l>My Gods and Mothers Reſurrections:</l>
            <l>Within the Spheres of which, two Bliſſes move,</l>
            <l>All I enjoy below, hope for above:</l>
            <l>But all my Words and Actions needs muſt be</l>
            <l>Lame Offerings, fit for <hi>Vulcan,</hi> not for Thee.</l>
            <l>I cannot ſing like <hi>David,</hi> nor can I</l>
            <l>Be even like <hi>Saul,</hi> when <hi>Saul</hi> did prophecy;</l>
            <l>Yet by that Harp which was his cure, I find</l>
            <l>A Tongue to eaſe my overjoyed Mind:</l>
            <l>Therefore my Song ſhall fill the thankful Quire,</l>
            <l>My Voice ſhall conſort with the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Lyre,</l>
            <l>To drown its Hoarſneſs in thoſe ſweeter Lays,</l>
            <l>So hiding my Defects, but not thy Praiſe.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="metrical_Psalms">
            <div n="116" type="Psalm">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:64837:39"/>
               <head>The <hi>CXVI.</hi> PSALM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>1</label> I Love to praiſe thy Love moſt high,</l>
                  <l>Who to my Praiſe gav'ſt ear;</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>2</label> While I have Breath, to thee I'le cry,</l>
                  <l>For thou my Cry did'ſt hear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>3</label> Hell's Priſon made my Soul afraid,</l>
                  <l>Death's Snares beſet me round;</l>
                  <l>'Till to thy Name I ſought for aid,</l>
                  <l>Nothing but Woes I found.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>4</label> But when I pray'd, Lord eaſe my Woe,</l>
                  <l>O Lord! ſave thou my Soul;</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>5</label> His Grace and Goodneſs God did ſhow,</l>
                  <l>Making his Patient whole.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>6</label> His Love and Juſtice is diſplay'd,</l>
                  <l>Shiclding the lowly'ſt Head;</l>
                  <l>And raiſing mine, whom Grief had laid</l>
                  <l>Down low, even near the Dead.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>7</label> Then Soul, ſaid I, gad not abroad,</l>
                  <l>To loſe thy ſought-for Reſt:</l>
                  <l>Thou ſeeſt Love fills the Heart of God;</l>
                  <l>O make that Love thy Hoſt!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>8</label> That Love, which keeps thee from the Grave,</l>
                  <l>Thy Foot from falls, thine Eye</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>9</label> From Tears, and gives thee Life to have</l>
                  <l>This ſpent in Piety.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>10</label> Thus I believ'd, and therefore pray'd,</l>
                  <l>'Till Troubles ſhook my Truſt;</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>11</label> Then raſhly ſaid, all Men are made</l>
                  <l>Of Falſhood, as of Duſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>12</label> But what bring I to thee? I'le take</l>
                  <l>The Cup of Bleſſing, Lord;</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>13</label> And bleſs thy Name, whoſe Mercies make</l>
                  <l>Our Duty our Reward.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>14</label> I'le pay my Vows in ſight of them,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Lives moſt holy are;</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>15</label> Whoſe Deaths are in thine Eyes eſteem,</l>
                  <l>(As its own ſight) moſt dear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>16</label> Thy Handmaid's Son, thy Servant Lord,</l>
                  <l>Thy Servant, Lord, am I!</l>
                  <l>Bound faſter to thee by the Cord,</l>
                  <l>Which thou art pleas'd t'unty.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:64837:39"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>17</label> I'le offer ſtill unto thy Name</l>
                  <l>My Life, my Praiſe, my Prayer;</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>18</label> I'le pay my Vows in ſight of them,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Lives moſt holy are.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To God the Father, God the Son,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And God the Holy-Ghoſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Be Glory; and let every one</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Strive who ſhall praiſe God moſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>HALLELUJAH.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="Psalm">
               <head>The <hi>XXVII.</hi> PSALM.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>LUCE <hi>tuâ fruamur</hi> LUCE.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>1</label> GOD is my Soul's dear Light,</l>
                  <l>What ſhould I fear but him?</l>
                  <l>God is my Life's chief Health and Might,</l>
                  <l>What elſe ſhould dreadful ſeem?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>2</label> When wicked ones (my Foes)</l>
                  <l>Approach me to devour,</l>
                  <l>They ſhall fall down, for they that roſe</l>
                  <l>Have fall'n into my Pow'r.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>3</label> Though many Troops beſiege,</l>
                  <l>None ſhall my Heart diſmay;</l>
                  <l>Though Men againſt me Battel pitch,</l>
                  <l>God's ſtrength ſhall be my ſtay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>4</label> This only Grace, this boon</l>
                  <l>Of God I now deſire;</l>
                  <l>That in his Houſe I may have room</l>
                  <l>To pray in, and retire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>5</label> There I his Pleaſure taſt,</l>
                  <l>I have his ſhelter there;</l>
                  <l>There on a Rock I ſhall be plac'd</l>
                  <l>In times of Grief and Care.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>6</label> For all my Foes ſurround,</l>
                  <l>When God their Siege hath rais'd;</l>
                  <l>Around his Courts with joyful ſound,</l>
                  <l>God ſhall be greatly prais'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>7</label> O therefore hear me, Lord,</l>
                  <l>When I rejoyce or cry!</l>
                  <l>Comfort or Mercy ſtill afford,</l>
                  <l>And to my Call reply.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>8</label> When once it heard thy Grace,</l>
                  <l>my Heart to thee could ſpeak;</l>
                  <l>O Lord, thou ſaid'ſt, <hi>Seek ye my Face!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy Face, Lord, will I ſeek.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>9</label> Thy Face O never hide,</l>
                  <l>Nor turn it once away!</l>
                  <l>O Leave me not, my God, my Guide,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſtrenth is all my ſtay!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>10</label> When Friends no care had took,</l>
                  <l>Thou didſt for me provide;</l>
                  <l>Nay, when my Parents me forſook,</l>
                  <l>Thou laid'ſt me not aſide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>11</label> Lord, teach me thy plain way,</l>
                  <l>To ſhun each crooked Path;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe my Foes would have me ſtray,</l>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>12</label> O ſave me from their wrath!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>See how the Faithleſs riſe</l>
                  <l>Againſt me, and their Breath</l>
                  <l>Would firſt enſnare by Calumnies,</l>
                  <l>Then cut me off by Death.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>13</label> Lord, I had fainted quite,</l>
                  <l>Had I not hop'd to ſee</l>
                  <l>Thy Goodneſs in this Life, to light</l>
                  <l>My Soul t' Eternity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>14</label> Wait then on God, poor Soul!</l>
                  <l>Take Courage, kiſs his Rod;</l>
                  <l>For he ſhall make thee ſtrong, and whole,</l>
                  <l>Wait then I ſay on God.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Glory and Praiſe allow</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To God in Trinity,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As at the firſt he was, is now,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And evermore ſhall be.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="Psalm">
               <head>The <hi>XXIII.</hi> PSALM Paraphras'd.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE King of Heav'n, the God of Love,</l>
                  <l>Takes up a Shepherd's Crook;</l>
                  <l>(As <hi>David</hi> did) his Son above,</l>
                  <l>To his few Sheep will look:</l>
                  <l>Then, though in Deſerts they are left,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.20.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>How ſafe are thoſe few Sheep!</l>
                  <l>How ſafe am I from wolviſh Theft,</l>
                  <l>Where Chriſt the Fold doth keep.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:64837:40"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>For while I wake, he lets me feed</l>
                  <l>By th' Sunſhine of his Eye;</l>
                  <l>When I want Reſt, (if ought I need)</l>
                  <l>His Arm's my Canopy:</l>
                  <l>So that I ſhall not fear Death's Night;</l>
                  <l>Nay, when Time's Bell has gone,</l>
                  <l>Darkneſs (that harbours many a Sp'rite)</l>
                  <l>Shall let my Soul alone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My Soul,<note place="margin">Return.</note> array'd then in its Light,</l>
                  <l>Such Glories ſhall put on,</l>
                  <l>As they that make my Shepherd white,</l>
                  <l>Who is my Shield, and Sun.</l>
                  <l>He from a howling Wilderneſs,</l>
                  <l>(Of Savages th' Aboad)</l>
                  <l>Hath brought me by his right Addreſs</l>
                  <l>Into fair <hi>Canaan</hi>'s Road.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There up and down meek Lambs he leads,</l>
                  <l>While Tides of Joy flow by;</l>
                  <l>Can his Flock want, who kindly feeds</l>
                  <l>Young Ravens, when they cry?</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Leader by the Flood,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>He bids his Army ſtay;</l>
                  <l>Then (as he gave <hi>Elijah</hi> Food)<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.8.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>He cheers them in their way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The pow'r and goodneſs of our God<note place="margin">Return.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are our advance and ſtay;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.16.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s Staff, and <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Rod;<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.29.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Do Wonders leſs than they:</l>
                  <l>They ſave the Poor, ſupport the Weak;</l>
                  <l>Heal ſick Folks, help the Blind:</l>
                  <l>Soft Hearts they bead, hard ones they break;</l>
                  <l>Thus nurturing the Unking.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For all <hi>Saul</hi>'s envy, <hi>Doeg</hi>'s hate,</l>
                  <l>My Head and Beard is crown'd;</l>
                  <l>In ſpite of Foes I fit in ſtate,</l>
                  <l>With Eaſe and Plenty round.</l>
                  <l>My Bowl's with Wine ſwell'd to the brim,</l>
                  <l>With Oyl my Temples ſhine;</l>
                  <l>God is with me, e're I with him;</l>
                  <l>His Goodneſs 'tis, not mine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His Grace (and not their own) anoints<note place="margin">Return.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Kings, to the ſway they bear;</l>
                  <l>His Spirit Royal Feaſts appoints,</l>
                  <l>His Son is our beſt Cheer.</l>
                  <l>O that towards God my days could move</l>
                  <l>Faſt, as to Death they tend!</l>
                  <l>My Thanks ſhould keep pace with his Love,</l>
                  <l>And (like it) never</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:64837:40"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
